<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?><feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'><title>Frank's Movie Log</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/feed.xml' rel='self' /><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com' /><updated>2014-12-01T01:28:13-05:00</updated><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com</id><author><name>Frank Showalter</name></author><entry><title>11. The Road to Singapore (1931) ★★½☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-road-to-singapore-1931/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-road-to-singapore-1931</id><updated>2014-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a shot in &lt;em&gt;The Road to Singapore&lt;/em&gt; that sums up the film. It&amp;#39;s night. Cross-fade from natives pounding jungle drums to a woman gazing out her bedroom window. The camera then pans out, away from her window, and up, across acres and acres of dark jungle to settle behind a man standing on his porch, gazing at the woman’s bungalow in the distance.
Now granted, the shot&amp;#39;s tracking over an obvious paper mache model, but kudos to director Alfred Green for trying. This is a movie whose reach simply exceeds its grasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The woman in the shot is Doris Kenyon. She plays Phillipa. The man is William Powell. He plays Hugh. The setting is Khota, a small tropical island in the Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phillipa is caught in an unhappy marriage to the local doctor. She wants him to sweep her off her feet, he wants her to find his socks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugh has just returned to the island after supposedly running off with another man’s wife. Hugh and Phillipa flirt. Her resolve weakens. Things come to a head when Phillipa, believing her husband to be out of town, accepts an invitation from Hugh to dine at his bungalow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At it’s heart, &lt;em&gt;The Road to Singapore&lt;/em&gt; is the story of an ill-conceived marriage. One helped along to dissolution by a preponderance of melodrama and jungle drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It tries for passionate drama, and might have come close for its time. Of course, it feels timid now. It has some bad moments, such as when its characters slip into that era’s favorite affectation of delivering their lines while staring off at nothing in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the film is entertaining thanks to Powell’s performance. Despite the subject matter, the film gives him ample opportunities to showcase his comedic timing. He ambles through much of the film exuding the urbane wit and charm that would become his trademark. He wins us over just as he wins over Phillipa. After all, who else could look at home in the jungle, dressed in a tuxedo?&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>10. British Intelligence (1940) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/british-intelligence-1940/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/british-intelligence-1940</id><updated>2014-10-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Fair warning, I’m going to spoil the entire plot of &lt;em&gt;British Intelligence&lt;/em&gt;. I see no other way to review the film. Plot is all it has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s World War I and the British are hurting. The Germans seem to know every move they’re about to make before they make it. The British suspect someone in their organization is the famed German spy Strendler. But no one knows what Strendler looks like. The British resolve to pull their best spy out from undercover field duty to weed out Strendler. But even that plan leaks to the Germans, who kill the British agent and shoot down his extraction plane. The pilot, Frank Bennett, survives and we see him in a hospital being tended to by a nurse, Helene von Lorbeer (Margaret Lindsay). There’s an attraction between the two, but she says she has to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Von Lorbeer turns out to be a German spy. She’s recalled to headquarters, given a commendation and a new assignment. Posing as a refugee, she’s to infiltrate the house of British cabinet minister Arthur Bennett. Arthur is, of course, Frank’s father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Von Lorbeer ingratiates herself with the Bennett family. Her contact is the family butler Valdar (Boris Karloff). Unbeknownst to von Lorbeer, Valdar is a double-agent, reporting to the head of British Intelligence. After some sloppy code-passing, British Intelligence begin to suspect von Lorbeer. They set a trap involving a would-be German agent, but von Lorbeer sees through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The return of Frank Bennett prompts von Lorbeer to reveal that she’s actually a &lt;em&gt;British&lt;/em&gt; agent. Valdar overhears this and forces von Lorbeer into the cellar at gunpoint. Von Lorbeer explains that she had to make up the British agent story to allay Frank’s suspicions. After showing the commendation award she received from German command, Valdar believes her story and admits that he is, in fact, Strendler. Further, the British cabinet are meeting upstairs and Valdar plans to blow up the house under the guise of a Zeppelin bombing. He’s even stolen the plans for the next British offensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the authorities have Valdar under surveillance and they rush into the cellar in time to disarm the bomb. Valdar flees with the plans. He’s shot during his escape but makes it to a German safe house. Just as they’re about to transmit the plans, a Zeppelin bomb levels the building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a lot of plot. The labyrinthine twists of agents, double agents, and triple agents, leaves little room for characterization. But maybe that’s by design. Characterization requires some degree of plausibility, and the more one thinks about this film, the more it devolves into a series of flimsy revelations and deus ex machina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider Valdar’s big reveal that he is Strendler. If Valdar was working for the British he would have told them about von Lorbeer, making the ruse involving the fake German agent unnecessary. But if Valdar didn’t tell the British about von Lorbeer, how did they know her handler’s code phrases? Surely, things like that wouldn’t be reused between agents. And just how did Valdar acquire so much information? It would seem that his intelligence gathering consists of little-more than standing outside thin doors or open windows. As a butler he wouldn’t be privy to any intelligence discussed at a secure location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse still, even at only an hour and six minutes, &lt;em&gt;British Intelligence&lt;/em&gt; is too long. The whole opening sequence only serves to introduce Frank Bennett and he disappears for the rest of the film, only showing up for a few minutes just before the end. Why not start with von Lorbeer undercover? She’d be a sympathetic character we’d actually care about, at least until her reveal as a German spy, which would have been a good one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least Karloff is good in what amounts to a triple role. It&amp;#39;s nice to see him work outside the horror genre, but he can’t save this mess.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>9. For the Defense (1930) ★★½☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/for-the-defense-1930/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/for-the-defense-1930</id><updated>2014-10-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the Defense&lt;/em&gt; stars William Powell as Bill Foster. Bill is a slick defense lawyer famous for using any technicality or loophole to get his clients an acquittal, despite their obvious guilt. He’s so well-respected in the underworld that, when his car’s stolen, the crooks return it after getting a look at the registration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill’s seeing a showgirl, Irene, played by Kay Francis. Irene wants Bill to marry her, but Bill says he&amp;#39;s not the marrying kind. Irene&amp;#39;s also seeing another guy, Jack, behind Bill&amp;#39;s back. Jack’s a nice-enough guy, but he lacks Bill’s swagger. Jack wants to marry Irene, but Irene just strings him along,  hoping Bill will change his mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early one morning, Irene’s driving Jack home. The two have been out all night and Jack’s pie-eyed drunk. Jack gropes at her, causing her to hit and kill a stranded motorist. Recognizing what it would do to her reputation, were she discovered out with him at the early hour, Jack insists she flee the scene. Jack stays and takes the rap for the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irene persuades Bill to take Jacks’s case. But as the evidence comes to light, Bill realizes Irene was out with Jack. Things look bad for Jack. Soon, Bill realizes he’ll have to chose between Irene’s reputation and Jack’s liberty. Irene wants to take the stand to exonerate Jack, but Bill won’t let her ruin her reputation. There’s another option, but it means crossing a line Bill had set for himself and risking everything he’s worked for in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As melodramas go, &lt;em&gt;For the Defense&lt;/em&gt; isn’t a bad one. Early on, when Bill’s riding high, his urbane charm, affinity for alcohol, and underworld connections foreshadow Powell’s famous turn as Nick Charles in the &lt;em&gt;Thin Man&lt;/em&gt; series of films. Francis plays well opposite him and doesn’t overact her part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the film sees both of them delivering lines and, mid-sentence, turning to gaze at nothing in particular for dramatic effect. It’s an annoying affectation that mars an otherwise passable hour and five minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and look fast for Gabby Hayes in an uncredited bit-part as a speakeasy waiter.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>8. A Walk Among the Tombstones (2014) ★½☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/a-walk-among-the-tombstones-2014/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/a-walk-among-the-tombstones-2014</id><updated>2014-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Walk Among the Tombstones&lt;/em&gt; has the potential to be good, but it never comes together. Too much gets in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot is a hodgepodge of cop-thriller clichés. The protagonist is Matthew Scudder, played by Liam Neeson. Scudder is a recovering alcoholic and ex-cop. Scudder quit the force after gunning down a gang of street toughs who tried to hold up his neighborhood bar. His superiors called him a hero and gave him a commendation. Scudder quit anyway. He quit drinking too. Later, we learn his actions weren&amp;#39;t quite so heroic. It&amp;#39;s supposed to be a revelation, but anyone who&amp;#39;s seen more than a few cop movies will see it coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scudder now makes his living as an unlicensed private investigator. He takes the case of a drug trafficker who’s wife was kidnapped, raped, tortured and killed. The trail leads him to a pair of horrific sociopaths who’ve been doing this for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the part of the movie that had potential. We see Scudder work the case even as the killers stalk their next target. It&amp;#39;s dark, gritty and even a little creepy. But like I said, things get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Scudder acquiring a sidekick in the form of TJ, a street-smart homeless boy. TJ has sickle-cell anemia, a plot point that seems to exist as a cheap way to generate audience sympathy as well as enable the improbable third act. Of course, this leads to the tired sub-plot where the plucky street-kid breaks through the gruff ex-cop’s tough exterior. It goes nowhere and feels out of place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the movie wore on, I found myself getting more and more angry. The contempt for the audience&amp;#39;s intelligence is galling. Though meant for adults, the film treats us like children. Scudder verbalizes every clue, even when it makes no sense for him to do so. At one point, Scudder discovers some badly written romance fiction. He reads it aloud, even though he&amp;#39;s alone and the camera is looking at the page. This is a film that doesn’t even trust us to be able to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spoon-feeding of the plot results in lots of redundant scenes. The movie opens with one. Scudder sits in the car with his partner. The partner bemoans Scudder&amp;#39;s drinking, saying he worries he can’t count on Scudder to have his back. Scudder gets out of the car and walks into a bar. It’s morning. He grabs a paper and sits down. Without a word the bartender brings Scudder a coffee and two shots of whiskey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not just open with Scudder walking into the bar? The morning light, the lack of dialog, the coffee and two shots; they tell us everything we need to know. Not to mention we never see that partner again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to like this movie, I really did. I love a good detective story, and the film even name-checks Sam Spade and Phillip Marlowe. But it follows that with a joke based on a dated football reference that wouldn&amp;#39;t be funny even if it were current.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few minutes on Wikipedia tells me that the film is a combination of several novels by Lawrence Block. Maybe the film tried to condense too many plot-points into a single movie, or maybe the books were just bad. Whatever the reason, it&amp;#39;s pretty damning that Liam Neeson’s would-be New York accent is the least of this film&amp;#39;s problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>7. Blue Ruin (2013) ★★★★☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/blue-ruin-2013/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/blue-ruin-2013</id><updated>2014-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Consider the novelty of &lt;em&gt;Blue Ruin&lt;/em&gt;. There are no explosions, no car chases, and the only gunfight happens off-screen. And yet, it&amp;#39;s a terrifically tense and visceral experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story follows Dwight, a homeless man living on the Delaware coast. When we first meet him, Dwight is taking a bath inside of an empty single-family home. Just as he gets comfortable, Dwight hears the owners arrive and hurries out of the house. It’s an elegant metaphor. As we’ll learn, Dwight has spent much of his adult life running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One morning, Dwight is roused by the local police, who take Dwight to the station. Dwight isn’t in trouble, but the officers have news and want him to be in a safe place when he hears it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The man who killed Dwight’s mother and father is getting an early parole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwight takes the news with an eerie calm. He returns to the rusty car he sleeps in, replaces the battery, fills up the tank, and heads home. Home is a small town in the mountains of Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwight travels to the local prison. He arrives in time to see Will Cleland, the man who murdered his parents, walk free. From his car, Dwight watches the Cleland clan arrive in a white limousine to greet Will. In Dwight&amp;#39;s expression we see the mix of bile and nausea churning in his gut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwight follows the limo to a nearby dive bar. He sneaks in through the back door and waits in the mens room. We see the fear in his eyes. Dwight wanted a gun, but all he could afford was the small shiv in his sweaty hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, Will enters and Dwight exacts his revenge.  It’s a brutal, clumsy bit of violence that leaves Dwight blood-soaked and shaken. Dwight sneaks out of the bar and pops the limo’s tire with his shiv, gashing his hand in the process. It&amp;#39;s another metaphor. There are no clean getaways. Dwight returns to his car and reaches for his keys…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they’re not there. Dwight lost them in the fight. It’s a plot point that should feel predictable and forced, but here, like so much of the movie, it feels natural. Almost inescapable. Dwight steals the limo and makes his escape, flat tire and all, but he knows the police will trace his car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings Dwight to his estranged sister. Their meeting communicates volumes about Dwight’s state of mind. After their parents death, Dwight disappeared, opting to drop out of society rather than face his grief. His sister has grieved and moved on.  She has two small children Dwight has never met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the course of their meeting, Dwight realizes that his actions weren&amp;#39;t reported to the police. Meaning the Cleland&amp;#39;s intend to exact revenge on their own. Dwight and his sister rush back to her home to check on her kids. They’re safe, but Dwight knows the Clelands will track the car back to his sister’s house where it’s registered. He convinces her to take her family and leave town. Then Dwight waits for the inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blue Ruin&lt;/em&gt; is a straightforward rural noir. There aren’t any flashbacks or quirky characters. There are no cinematic allusions or pop-culture references. It’s a simple story told well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, almost. Fair warning, I’m about to nitpick what’s otherwise a great film, and in the process, spoil a couple of plot points. If you haven’t seen the movie, I encourage you to give it a look, then come back and read the rest of this review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still here? Okay, here goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember when Ben takes Dwight back to his isolated cabin? Dwight asks Ben if he’s a hunter, and Ben replies no, he mostly does target shooting. For a film that’s so judicious with it’s dialog, one that does such a good job &lt;em&gt;showing&lt;/em&gt; us things, this feels sloppy. Because now we know that Ben is going to snipe the guy in Dwight’s car. If a gun is introduced in Act 1 it must go off by Act 3. It&amp;#39;s the only plot point that feels cinematic instead of organic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it&amp;#39;s one line. I told you I was going to nitpick. But the next issue is a bit bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwight’s parents were killed because Dwight’s father fell in love with Will Cleland&amp;#39;s mother. Watching the movie, this seems plausible enough, but in retrospect it doesn’t hold up. We see the Cleland family. We see the children. They&amp;#39;re foaming-at-the-mouth backwoods psychos. They keep machine guns duct taped under the living room recliner. We also see Dwight and his sister. We see that Dwight has never handled a gun. It begs a question: How does Dwight&amp;#39;s father, a man who raised such a meek family, get together with the kind of woman who would marry the backwoods, gun-crazy Cleland patriarch?  The characters tell us it happened, but the movie shows us nothing to support it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bits only stand out because the rest of the film feels so authentic and true. It&amp;#39;s not perfect, but it&amp;#39;s damn close.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>6. The Boogie Man Will Get You (1942) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-boogie-man-will-get-you-1942/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-boogie-man-will-get-you-1942</id><updated>2014-09-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Boogie Man Will Get You&lt;/em&gt; is not a good film. But for fans of Boris Karloff and Peter Lorre, it is, at times, an entertaining one. Despite the title, it is not a horror movie, but rather a dark comedy in the vein of &lt;em&gt;Arsenic and Old Lace (1944)&lt;/em&gt;. And to that end, Karloff and Lorre make a fine pair of lovable murderers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karloff plays Nathaniel Billings, an eccentric but earnest old professor who spends his days working in his basement laboratory. Along comes Winnie, a young divorcee who wants to buy Billings’ crumbling tavern home and turn it into an inn. Billings agrees to sell, provided he can stay on and complete his experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Winnie doesn&amp;#39;t know that Billings’ experiments involve trying to create an army of atomic supermen to win the war. Or that his test subjects consist of the various traveling salesmen that knock on his door. Or that all his experiments have been fatal failures, leaving him with a nice collection of well-preserved corpses. One would think this sort of thing would have come up during the walk-through, but the film gives Winnie the mental acuity of a toddler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorre plays Arthur Lorencz, a smarmy opportunist who&amp;#39;s the town doctor, mayor, mortician, notary, and everything else. He holds the mortgage on Billings’ home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a great scene where Lorencz, in his capacity as town sheriff, confronts Billings about one of the traveling salesman&amp;#39;s corpses. With idyllic pride, Billings explains his experiments. Lorencz is relieved. Never mind the corpse, Billings’  experiments could be worth a fortune! Soon they’re partners bemoaning the lack of quality “test subjects”. It’s a terrific bit that hints at the film’s potential as a subversive black comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that potential is never realized. Instead, the film devolves into an outright farce. The finale sees the cast held hostage in Karloff&amp;#39;s laboratory by an escaped fascist planning to blow up a nearby munitions depot. Because, what better spot to open an inn than next to a munitions depot?&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>5. Black Legion (1937) ★★½☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/black-legion-1937/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/black-legion-1937</id><updated>2014-08-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Bogart plays Frank Taylor, a senior machinist and family man who&amp;#39;s in line for a rich promotion to foreman. To Frank&amp;#39;s shock, he&amp;#39;s passed over in favor of a younger coworker named Dombrowski. Feeling angry and cheated, Frank falls in with the titular Legion, a black-robed hate group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Legion runs Dombrowski out of town and Frank ascends to foreman. Things are great until Frank&amp;#39;s Legion-mandated recruiting activities lead to an accident at the shop. Frank is demoted in favor of his neighbor. Once again, the Legion come to Frank&amp;#39;s aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secrecy and violence begin to wear on Frank. He starts to drink heavily. His wife leaves him, taking their young son. Frank takes up with the local floozy. One night, drunk and despondent, Frank confesses everything to his longtime friend Ed (Dick Foran). After sobering up, Frank panics and tells the Legion what he&amp;#39;s done. The Legion kidnap Ed, but things don&amp;#39;t go as planned, leaving Frank with blood on his hands and nowhere to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bogart shines in what should have been a break-out role. The script&amp;#39;s multi-faceted depiction of the Legion is enlightening. We see the radio demagogues cultivating resentment and fear. We see how that fear drives Legion membership. Finally, we see how that membership feeds the profiteers behind the scenes who cash in on the sales of Legion uniforms and revolvers. But Frank going from honest family-man to drunken womanizer in what seems like a matter of weeks is a stretch. It gives the film a trite, after-school-special feel that undermines the still-relevant social context.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>4. Psycho-Circus (1967) ★★½☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/psycho-circus-1967/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/psycho-circus-1967</id><updated>2014-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Circus of Fear&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Psycho Circus&lt;/em&gt;, here in the US) opens with a shot of Klaus Kinski&amp;#39;s wrist watch. He&amp;#39;s part of a group of thieves preparing to execute a daylight holdup of an armored car as it crosses London&amp;#39;s Tower bridge. There&amp;#39;s no dialog. The crooks work on a precise timetable. Two men setup a road block to divert oncoming traffic, then rush to setup the escape route. Two others take out the escort car and maneuver the armored car to the other side of the bridge. Kinski knocks out the bridge operator and raises the bridge. Everything goes according to plan until one of the thieves panics and shoots one of the guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, one can imagine theater-goers in 1966 wondering if they were in the right theater. There&amp;#39;s no sign of a circus or top-billed Christopher Lee. As if to assure those confused patrons, the opening titles fade in as the crooks make good on their escape. There&amp;#39;s even a catchy title theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the rest of the film never matches this inspired opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out the entire heist was a MacGuffin. In the span of a few minutes, all the crooks, save Kinski, are killed off. This was a German co-production and Kinski was a big star in Germany. He seems to be here strictly for name recognition, as he spends the rest of the movie doing nothing but lurking about in the shadows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setting shifts to the winter home of the Barberini circus. The pacing slows. Things get talky. Over twenty minutes in, Christopher Lee finally shows up as a lion tamer who spends most of the film wearing a black balaclava. Leo Genn plays a police inspector trying to find the stolen money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, the movie devolves into an unremarkable whodunit. An unseen, knife-throwing assailant picks off potential suspects.  There are lots of red herrings and at least one plot twist you&amp;#39;ll likely see coming before everything is wrapped up. All well and good, but a much more interesting mystery is what the cast and crew could have done with a better script.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>3. The Bloody Judge (1970) ★½☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-bloody-judge-1970/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-bloody-judge-1970</id><updated>2014-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not a good sign when the making-of featurette on the DVD is more interesting than the feature film, but such is the case with &lt;em&gt;The Bloody Judge&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film is set in England during the final days of King James II. George Jeffreys, the titular Bloody Judge (played by Christopher Lee), was a real historical figure who meted out death sentences to suppress the burgeoning rebellion, only to end up on the wrong side of the revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the making-of featurette, Lee correctly refers to this period as the Bloody Assizes. He saw Jeffreys as a kind of Jekyll-and-Hyde figure. On the one hand, a brilliant legal mind who rose to become the highest justice in the land. On the other, a merciless executioner who sentenced hundreds to their deaths. If the film had focused on this dichotomy, it might have turned out much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, most of the screen time belongs to a group of fictitious characters. There&amp;#39;s Mary, a peasant girl Jeffreys obsesses over. And Harry, Mary&amp;#39;s lover. Besides Mary&amp;#39;s affections, Harry has connections to the rebels, doubly infuriating Jeffreys. But Harry is the son of Lord Wessex, a sometime friend of Jeffreys, which makes things tricky. The film revolves around this triangle. Jeffreys orders Mary arrested. Harry frees her. Jeffreys captures them both. They escape. Then the revolution happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and there&amp;#39;s a blind oracle who may or may not be psychic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logic behind all these side-plots become clear in the DVD supplement. The film had a slew of financing sources and each financier wanted a different kind of film. One wanted a horror movie. One wanted a historical drama. One wanted an exploitation picture. At least no one wanted a comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making things even worse, Lee and director Jesús Franco disagreed on how Jeffreys should be played. Lee wanted to be faithful to history.  Franco wanted something more &amp;quot;dynamic.&amp;quot; I don&amp;#39;t know what he meant by &amp;quot;dynamic&amp;quot; and I don&amp;#39;t think Lee did either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting mis-mash is surprisingly boring. Think long, ponderous scenes full of exposition interspersed with the occasional sequence of Howard Vernon dressed like Boris Karloff in &lt;em&gt;The Tower of London (1939)&lt;/em&gt; torturing a semi-nude woman covered in Technicolor blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re in it for these exploitation sequences, I recommend liberal use of the fast-forward button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disparate financing also explains the myriad of alternate titles. In the US it was known as &lt;em&gt;Night of the Blood Monster&lt;/em&gt;. In England it was &lt;em&gt;Witch Killer of Broadmoor&lt;/em&gt;. Note that there is no Broadmoor in the film. Granted, there&amp;#39;s no Blood Monster either, but why Broadmoor? That&amp;#39;s one question the making-of featurette couldn&amp;#39;t answer.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>2. Stake Land (2010) ★★★☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/stake-land-2010/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/stake-land-2010</id><updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stake Land&lt;/em&gt; is set in a near-future where vamps (a kind of fast-running-zombie/vampire hybrid) have overrun the world. Enigmatic loner Mister takes in orphaned teen Martin. The pair head out in Mister&amp;#39;s old Cadillac in search of the fabled land of New Eden. Along the way, they run up against a fundamentalist neo-nazi militia that uses vamps as a kind of chemical weapon, dropping them out of helicopters into neighboring towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a grisly opening sequence where we see a vamp drain and discard the corpse of an infant, &lt;em&gt;Stake Land&lt;/em&gt; keeps its baddies off-screen as much as possible. Instead, it&amp;#39;s content to let the scenery establish atmosphere. Deserted strip malls. Desolate two-lane blacktops. Overgrown buildings. Rusted scrapheaps. An urban wilderness. It&amp;#39;s like a western with a super-bloody third act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#39;s not perfect. The voiceover narration is unnecessary. And co-writer Nick Damici, who plays Mister, spends much of the film wearing sunglasses. This is good because his eyes betray his grizzled facade. Warren Oates would have been perfect. If he were forty years younger and not dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stake Land&lt;/em&gt; may not be a revelation, but it is a solid entry in the post-apocalyptic horror genre. The script respects the audience. When Martin hears that his family is &amp;quot;already dead,&amp;quot; he accepts it with wisdom seldom seen in horror films. The production values and supporting performances belie the film&amp;#39;s all but straight-to-video release. And come on, &lt;em&gt;the bad guys drop vampires out of helicopters&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>