<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?><feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'><title>Frank's Movie Log</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/feed.xml' rel='self' /><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com' /><updated>2014-09-19T23:32:24-04:00</updated><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com</id><author><name>Frank Showalter</name></author><entry><title>6. The Boogie Man Will Get You (1942)★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-boogie-man-will-get-you-1942' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.comreviews/the-boogie-man-will-get-you-1942</id><updated>2014-09-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Boogie Man Will Get You&lt;/em&gt; is not a good film. But for fans of Boris Karloff and Peter Lorre, it is, at times, an entertaining one. Despite the title, it is not a horror movie, but rather a dark comedy in the vein of &lt;em&gt;Arsenic and Old Lace (1944)&lt;/em&gt;. And to that end, Karloff and Lorre make a fine pair of lovable murderers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karloff plays Nathaniel Billings, an eccentric but earnest old professor who spends his days working in his basement laboratory. Along comes Winnie, a young divorcee who wants to buy Billings’ crumbling tavern home and turn it into an inn. Billings agrees to sell, provided he can stay on and complete his experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Winnie doesn&amp;#39;t know that Billings’ experiments involve trying to create an army of atomic supermen to win the war. Or that his test subjects consist of the various traveling salesmen that knock on his door. Or that all his experiments have been fatal failures, leaving him with a nice collection of well-preserved corpses. One would think this sort of thing would have come up during the walk-through, but the film gives Winnie the mental acuity of a toddler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorre plays Arthur Lorencz, a smarmy opportunist who&amp;#39;s the town doctor, mayor, mortician, notary, and everything else. He holds the mortgage on Billings’ home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a great scene where Lorencz, in his capacity as town sheriff, confronts Billings about one of the traveling salesman&amp;#39;s corpses. With idyllic pride, Billings explains his experiments. Lorencz is relieved. Never mind the corpse, Billings’  experiments could be worth a fortune! Soon they’re partners bemoaning the lack of quality “test subjects”. It’s a terrific bit that hints at the film’s potential as a subversive black comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that potential is never realized. Instead, the film devolves into an outright farce. The finale sees the cast held hostage in Karloff&amp;#39;s laboratory by an escaped fascist planning to blow up a nearby munitions depot. Because, what better spot to open an inn than next to a munitions depot?&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>5. Black Legion (1937)★★½☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/black-legion-1937' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.comreviews/black-legion-1937</id><updated>2014-08-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Bogart plays Frank Taylor, a senior machinist and family man who&amp;#39;s in line for a rich promotion to foreman. To Frank&amp;#39;s shock, he&amp;#39;s passed over in favor of a younger coworker named Dombrowski. Feeling angry and cheated, Frank falls in with the titular Legion, a black-robed hate group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Legion runs Dombrowski out of town and Frank ascends to foreman. Things are great until Frank&amp;#39;s Legion-mandated recruiting activities lead to an accident at the shop. Frank is demoted in favor of his neighbor. Once again, the Legion come to Frank&amp;#39;s aid. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secrecy and violence begin to wear on Frank. He starts to drink heavily. His wife leaves him, taking their young son. Frank takes up with the local floozy. One night, drunk and despondent, Frank confesses everything to his longtime friend Ed (Dick Foran). After sobering up, Frank panics and tells the Legion what he&amp;#39;s done. The Legion kidnap Ed, but things don&amp;#39;t go as planned, leaving Frank with blood on his hands and nowhere to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bogart shines in what should have been a break-out role. The script&amp;#39;s multi-faceted depiction of the Legion is enlightening. We see the radio demagogues cultivating resentment and fear. We see how that fear drives Legion membership. Finally, we see how that membership feeds the profiteers behind the scenes who cash in on the sales of Legion uniforms and revolvers. But Frank going from honest family-man to drunken womanizer in what seems like a matter of weeks is a stretch. It gives the film a trite, after-school-special feel that undermines the still-relevant social context. &lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>4. Psycho-Circus (1967)★★½☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/psycho-circus-1967' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.comreviews/psycho-circus-1967</id><updated>2014-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Circus of Fear&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Psycho Circus&lt;/em&gt;, here in the US) opens with a shot of Klaus Kinski&amp;#39;s wrist watch. He&amp;#39;s part of a group of thieves preparing to execute a daylight holdup of an armored car as it crosses London&amp;#39;s Tower bridge. There&amp;#39;s no dialog. The crooks work on a precise timetable. Two men setup a road block to divert oncoming traffic, then rush to setup the escape route. Two others take out the escort car and maneuver the armored car to the other side of the bridge. Kinski knocks out the bridge operator and raises the bridge. Everything goes according to plan until one of the thieves panics and shoots one of the guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, one can imagine theater-goers in 1966 wondering if they were in the right theater. There&amp;#39;s no sign of a circus or top-billed Christopher Lee. As if to assure those confused patrons, the opening titles fade in as the crooks make good on their escape. There&amp;#39;s even a catchy title theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the rest of the film never matches this inspired opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out the entire heist was a MacGuffin. In the span of a few minutes, all the crooks, save Kinski, are killed off. This was a German co-production and Kinski was a big star in Germany. He seems to be here strictly for name recognition, as he spends the rest of the movie doing nothing but lurking about in the shadows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setting shifts to the winter home of the Barberini circus. The pacing slows. Things get talky. Over twenty minutes in, Christopher Lee finally shows up as a lion tamer who spends most of the film wearing a black balaclava. Leo Genn plays a police inspector trying to find the stolen money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, the movie devolves into an unremarkable whodunit. An unseen, knife-throwing assailant picks off potential suspects.  There are lots of red herrings and at least one plot twist you&amp;#39;ll likely see coming before everything is wrapped up. All well and good, but a much more interesting mystery is what the cast and crew could have done with a better script.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>3. The Bloody Judge (1970)★½☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-bloody-judge-1970' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.comreviews/the-bloody-judge-1970</id><updated>2014-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not a good sign when the making-of featurette on the DVD is more interesting than the feature film, but such is the case with &lt;em&gt;The Bloody Judge&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film is set in England during the final days of King James II. George Jeffreys, the titular Bloody Judge (played by Christopher Lee), was a real historical figure who meted out death sentences to suppress the burgeoning rebellion, only to end up on the wrong side of the revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the making-of featurette, Lee correctly refers to this period as the Bloody Assizes. He saw Jeffreys as a kind of Jekyll-and-Hyde figure. On the one hand, a brilliant legal mind who rose to become the highest justice in the land. On the other, a merciless executioner who sentenced hundreds to their deaths. If the film had focused on this dichotomy, it might have turned out much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, most of the screen time belongs to a group of fictitious characters. There&amp;#39;s Mary, a peasant girl Jeffreys obsesses over. And Harry, Mary&amp;#39;s lover. Besides Mary&amp;#39;s affections, Harry has connections to the rebels, doubly infuriating Jeffreys. But Harry is the son of Lord Wessex, a sometime friend of Jeffreys, which makes things tricky. The film revolves around this triangle. Jeffreys orders Mary arrested. Harry frees her. Jeffreys captures them both. They escape. Then the revolution happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and there&amp;#39;s a blind oracle who may or may not be psychic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logic behind all these side-plots become clear in the DVD supplement. The film had a slew of financing sources and each financier wanted a different kind of film. One wanted a horror movie. One wanted a historical drama. One wanted an exploitation picture. At least no one wanted a comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making things even worse, Lee and director Jesús Franco disagreed on how Jeffreys should be played. Lee wanted to be faithful to history.  Franco wanted something more &amp;quot;dynamic.&amp;quot; I don&amp;#39;t know what he meant by &amp;quot;dynamic&amp;quot; and I don&amp;#39;t think Lee did either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting mis-mash is surprisingly boring. Think long, ponderous scenes full of exposition interspersed with the occasional sequence of Howard Vernon dressed like Boris Karloff in &lt;em&gt;The Tower of London (1939)&lt;/em&gt; torturing a semi-nude woman covered in Technicolor blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re in it for these exploitation sequences, I recommend liberal use of the fast-forward button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disparate financing also explains the myriad of alternate titles. In the US it was known as &lt;em&gt;Night of the Blood Monster&lt;/em&gt;. In England it was &lt;em&gt;Witch Killer of Broadmoor&lt;/em&gt;. Note that there is no Broadmoor in the film. Granted, there&amp;#39;s no Blood Monster either, but why Broadmoor? That&amp;#39;s one question the making-of featurette couldn&amp;#39;t answer.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>2. Stake Land (2010)★★½☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/stake-land-2010' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.comreviews/stake-land-2010</id><updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stake Land&lt;/em&gt; is set in a near-future where vamps (a kind of fast-running-zombie/vampire hybrid) have overrun the world. Enigmatic loner Mister takes in orphaned teen Martin. The pair head out in Mister&amp;#39;s old Cadillac in search of the fabled land of New Eden. Along the way, they run up against a fundamentalist neo-nazi militia that uses vamps as a kind of chemical weapon, dropping them out of helicopters into neighboring towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a grisly opening sequence where we see a vamp drain and discard the corpse of an infant, &lt;em&gt;Stake Land&lt;/em&gt; keeps its baddies off-screen as much as possible. Instead, it&amp;#39;s content to let the scenery establish atmosphere. Deserted strip malls. Desolate two-lane blacktops. Overgrown buildings. Rusted scrapheaps. An urban wilderness. It&amp;#39;s like a western with a super-bloody third act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#39;s not perfect. The voiceover narration is unnecessary. And co-writer Nick Damici, who plays Mister, spends much of the film wearing sunglasses. This is good because his eyes betray his grizzled facade. Warren Oates would have been perfect. If he were forty years younger and not dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stake Land&lt;/em&gt; may not be a revelation, but it is a solid entry in the post-apocalyptic horror genre. The script respects the audience. When Martin hears that his family is &amp;quot;already dead,&amp;quot; he accepts it with wisdom seldom seen in horror films. The production values and supporting performances belie the film&amp;#39;s all but straight-to-video release. And come on, &lt;em&gt;the bad guys drop vampires out of helicopters&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>1. Welcome Back</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/features/welcome-back' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/features/welcome-back</id><updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Hey there, Frank here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confession time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last review was over a year ago. The top of my to-review list is a movie I saw almost two years ago. And there&amp;#39;s over 200 movies after that one. I have fallen off the review wagon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry about that. The trouble is, I enjoy writing about movies, but I enjoy watching them even more. But I can&amp;#39;t do both at the same time. So the more movies I watched, the more my to-review list grew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except, that&amp;#39;s not the whole truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See, I also spent a lot of time tinkering with this site. My day job is software development, and I love coding almost as much as I love movies. So I went through several design iterations. I added splash images, transitions, and client-side sorting and filtering. The site looked pretty damn sweet. But while I was adding all those features, you know what I wasn&amp;#39;t doing? Writing reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;#39;m declaring review bankruptcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s that mean? Well, in a nutshell, I&amp;#39;m starting over. I&amp;#39;ve still got the list (over in the &lt;a href=&quot;/viewings&quot;&gt;viewing log&lt;/a&gt;) of everything I&amp;#39;ve seen since January 1st 2012, but I&amp;#39;m starting over on reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my goals when I started the site was to become a better writer by forcing myself to write more. But writing a review for every movie I watch isn&amp;#39;t going to help if the reviews are crap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a lot of them were crap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were crap because I churned them out to clear the queue. I watch too many movies to review them all. So now, instead of trying to review every movie I watch, I&amp;#39;ll aim for one review a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That schedule should allow me three drafts per review. My prior reviews were almost all first draft efforts. Three drafts give me time to polish the text while still forcing me to publish it instead of tinkering for draft after draft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to bring the focus back to the writing I redesigned the site again. The splash images and posters are gone, because finding and prepping them took a lot of time. Time better spent writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So welcome back. I hope you&amp;#39;ll give me a second chance. We&amp;#39;ve got close to a hundred years of cinema to cover and I&amp;#39;m pretty excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s get started&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>