<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
  <title>Frank's Movie Log</title>
  <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/feed.xml' rel='self' />
  <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/' />
  <updated>2014-06-08T21:14:10-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Frank Showalter</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>
      11. The Thin Man (1934) ★★★★½
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/the-thin-man-1934' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/the-thin-man-1934</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;Eccentric inventor Clyde Wynant is preparing to go into seclusion to work on a new project when he’s interrupted by a visit from his daughter Dorothy (O&amp;#39;Sullivan) who announces her engagement. Wynant hurries her out, but promises to return in time for her wedding. Wynant continues his preparations and discovers that the $50,000 in bonds he’d earmarked as a wedding present for Dorothy are missing. He storms over to the apartment of his mistress Julia, catching her in the arms of another man in the process. Wynant accuses her of the theft and threatens to turn her over to the police. Three months later Dorothy hasn’t heard from her father. While out at a restaurant, she recognizes former detective Nick Charles (Powell) and approaches him for help. Nick–happy in his new life of leisure with his heiress wife Nora (Loy)–is reluctant to get involved, but when circumstances pin a pair of murders on the still missing Wynant, Nick steps in and uncovers a buried skeleton along with a labyrinthine array of suspects and motives. The mystery culminates with New York’s finest corralling all the suspects to a dinner party thrown by Nick and Nora, where Nick ferrets out the true killer.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;The talky opening betrays the film’s B-movie production, with the script throwing enough plot and characters at us to fill an entire movie, but once Powell makes his appearance–in a posh restaurant bar, demonstrating to an impromptu-crowd how various cocktails demand unique shaking rhythms (Manhattans to a Fox-Trot, Bronxs to a Two-Step, and Dry Martinis to a Waltz)–the dialog goes from stilted to fluid, with Powell gliding through the film as the witty urbane charmer we all believe ourselves to be after a few drinks. There’s little real danger and the entire plot is little more than a MacGuffin to support Powell’s lyrical banter, which reaches it’s apex during the iconic dinner party scene. As Loy says, “It’s the best dinner I’ve ever listened to.”&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>
      10. The Blob (1988) ★★☆☆☆
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/the-blob-1988' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/the-blob-1988</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;Rebel loner Kevin Dillon subs for clean-cut Steve McQueen and the army isn’t quite the white knight it was in the 1958 original, but this remake hits all the same plot points as a group of teenagers struggle to save a disbelieving small town from a gelatinous ooze that consumes its victims while adding to its ever-increasing mass. Where this entry declares its creative independence is via its memorable and gruesome special effects. This blob doesn’t just assimilate its victims, it digests them.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Director Chuck Russell shows a sure hand establishing the small-town atmosphere, and the cast is competent, making for a passable popcorn monster flick, but the script’s insistence on recreating the scenes from the original film while still tweaking the story results in characters often acting with no clear motivation short of advancing the plot. While not a total wash, it is disappointing, especially given that the ending’s obligatory sequel setup is so promising.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>
      9. The Thing (1982) ★★★★½
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/the-thing-1982' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/the-thing-1982</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;At a remote Antarctic research station, a group of scientists and their helicopter pilot (Russell) discover they’ve been infiltrated by a parasitic alien organism that assimilates other life forms and subsequently imitates them. After calculating that the alien would assimilate all of humanity within three years it reached civilization, one of the scientists destroys the station’s communications and transport equipment, stranding the crew with the monster. Tensions rise and the men start to turn on one another, unsure who’s a man, and who’s a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Ostensibly a remake of Howard Hawks&amp;#39; The Thing from Another World (1951), Carpenter’s film is actually a superior adaptation of the source material (John W. Campbell, Jr.’s novella, Who Goes There?), delivering a near-perfect mix of psychological horror and monster movie set pieces. The special effects are gruesomely inventive. We see one character defibrillating another, only to have the man’s chest open and chomp the would-be rescuer’s arms off at the elbows. Yet, the movie isn’t just about the monster. There’s a very Hawks-ian feel to the characters and their fragile camaraderie, that, along with the desolate location photography and weathered set design, earns our buy-in right away. While there’s no way of knowing how Hawks would have reacted to the amped up gore, he certainly would have appreciated the Carpenter’s unsentimental approach to capturing the men’s working lives and relationships with one-another, as well as the honest ending.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>
      8. A Nightmare on Elm Street 3: Dream Warriors (1987) ★★½☆☆
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/a-nightmare-on-elm-street-3-dream-warriors-1987' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/a-nightmare-on-elm-street-3-dream-warriors-1987</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;Arquette plays Kristen, a teenager tormented by nightmares of a badly burned man with razors for fingers. When she wakes from one of her dreams to find her wrists slashed, her parents–believing it a suicide attempt–commit her to a local psychiatric hospital. There she meets a group of teens plagued by similar nightmares and Nancy (played by Langenkamp) a survivor of the first film who’s now a doctor. Nancy tells Kristen and the other children that they–like herself–are the last descendants of the men and women who originally killed the man in their dreams: Freddy Krueger. Nancy also breaks the bad news that dying a dream with Krueger equals death in the real world. Later, Kristen falls asleep and encounters Krueger. In a panic, she pulls Nancy into her dream, unaware she could to do so. The two manage to escape Krueger. Sensing an opportunity, Nancy teaches the kids how to fight back in their dreams, but Krueger manages to take one child hostage, rendering him comatose in the real world. Nancy mounts a rescue mission, using Kristen to pull all the kids into a group dream and final showdown with Krueger.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;This third installment in the franchise veers toward dark fantasy, with Krueger claiming victims in a variety of imaginative, fx-heavy ways. Early on he’s a giant snake looking to swallow his victim whole, later he’s a giant-sized puppet-master, manipulating his victim’s tendons like a marionette. There’s even a scene where he’s a Ray Harryhausen-esque stop-motion skeleton. The inventive visuals help to mitigate the flat dialog and wooden performances. The worst of which belongs to Arquette, who does little more than scream. At everything. All the time.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>
      7. Prometheus (2012/I) ★★★★☆
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/prometheus-2012-i' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/prometheus-2012-i</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;In the late 21st century, archeologist Rapace discovers a series of identical star charts amongst the ruins of several disparate ancient civilizations. Viewing this as an invitation from humanity’s forerunners, the elderly chair of the massive Weyland corporation funds an expedition to follow the charts deep into space to an earth-sized moon orbiting a massive planet. The crew travel in stasis, watched over by David, an android played by Fassbender who passes the time watching the dreams of the various crew-members and Lawrence of Arabia (1962). Upon landing, the crew discover the remains of what appears to be an ancient alien species with DNA that matches humans. Things go downhill fast, though, and the search for knowledge quickly devolves into a struggle for survival, as the Weyland corporation’s hidden motives and the true nature of the alien species become clear.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;More bombastic and action-driven than director Ridley Scott’s Alien (1979), but less so than James Cameron’s Aliens (1986), Scott’s return to the Alien universe is a philosophical sci-fi horror. The visual effects are amazing, with immersive environments that manage to impart feelings of dread and awe simultaneously. The central theme of man’s innate desire to understand his creation provides a great hook, though the film’s lack of concrete answers will be frustrating for some. This isn’t a film about where we came from, but one about the need to ask the question, as best illustrated by Fassbender’s character, David, an android who views himself superior to humans and thus can’t understand the desire to meet one’s maker. Which begs the question: What if, upon meeting our creator, we were unimpressed?&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>
      6. City of the Living Dead (1983) ★★★½☆
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/city-of-the-living-dead-1983' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/city-of-the-living-dead-1983</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;In a desolate church cemetery, Father Thomas hangs himself from an old oak tree. Medium Mary Woodhouse (MacColl) sees the act during a seance, convulses violently and drops dead from shock. Nosing for a story, reporter Peter Bell (George) attends Mary’s funeral. As the mourners trickle away, Peter lingers and Mary awakens in her coffin, very much alive and frantic to escape. Peter hears her scratching at the coffin lid–or likely thinks he does, thanks to Mary’s psychic talents–and frees her. Mary tells Peter about her vision, and how Thomas’s suicide was a sacrifice intended to open the gates of Hell. Peter is skeptical but curious, and agrees to travel with Mary to where she believes the gate to exist, a remote New England town called Dunwich. In Dunwich, people are starting to disappear thanks to the now undead Thomas, who claims a pair of teens in a horrific–albeit memorable–sequence. Peter and Mary arrive and eventually connect with the few locals with enough sense and luck to stay alive. Together, they head for the cemetery in a last-ditch effort to close the gate and avoid the apocalypse.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Fulci’s film, the first of his unofficial Gates of Hell trilogy (followed by The Beyond (1981) and The House by the Cemetery (1981)) is a blend of mystery and horror with MacColl and George trying to track down the source of her vision while Fabrizio Jovine’s Father Thomas racks up the victims in increasingly gory ways. The supernatural aspects of the plot defy logical explanation, with Jovine appearing and disappearing at will. It’s not a matter of lazy screenwriting, but a calculated measure to show the characters battling forces they can’t possibly understand. The resulting chaos only adds to the gut-wrenching sense of dread that Fulci cultivates throughout the picture, making this a must-see for horror fans and 80’s gore aficionados.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>
      5. Soldier in the Rain (1963) ★★★☆☆
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/soldier-in-the-rain-1963' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/soldier-in-the-rain-1963</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;Set on an army base during peacetime, the film follows Sergeant Eustis Clay (McQueen) and his idol, Master Sergeant Maxwell Slaughter (Gleason). Clay cooks up a series of dim-witted get-rich-quick schemes, which draw the ire of rival Sergeant Lenahan and MP Priest, frequently requiring some degree of intervention from Slaughter to keep Clay out of trouble. Clay dreams of going into business with Slaughter when their enlistments end, but Slaughter is comfortable with the easy life he’s built for himself in the peacetime army. Sensing Slaughter’s reluctance, Clay tries to temp him with the lures of civilian life by setting him up on a blind date with ditzy teenager Bobby Jo Pepperdine (Weld). Slaughter navigates the situation with tact, settling into a fatherly relationship with Pepperdine that somewhat mirrors his relationship with Clay. Things turn dark when Clay gets word that his beloved dog has died, and Lenahan and Priest bait a drunken Clay into a two-against-one barroom brawl that ends in tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Given that his most iconic performances feature a minimal amount of dialog, it’s jarring to see McQueen in such a motor-mouth role, but he plays well opposite Gleason, whose disarming performance makes the film. And what an odd little film it is. After opening like a sitcom it gradually morphs into a drama, reflecting McQueen’s character’s own gradual maturity. Kudos to screenwriters Edwards and Richlin for keeping Goldman’s ending. Without it, the film would be a forgettable popcorn piece. As it turned out, the film was forgotten anyway, having the ill fortune to open five days after JFK’s assassination.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>
      4. Men Are Such Fools (1938) ★½☆☆☆
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/men-are-such-fools-1938' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/men-are-such-fools-1938</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;Lane plays a Linda, an ambitious secretary out to climb the corporate ladder. Just as her career takes off, she marries Jimmy, an ex-footballer from Princeton played by Morris, who demands she leave her job. Linda reluctantly agrees, and several months later they’ve settled into a bland suburban existence with Linda playing the role of dutiful housewife. Still ambitious, Linda arranges a promotion for Jimmy and leaves him when he turns it down, moving back to the city and resuming her career. Soon, she’s near the top of the ladder, working long nights alongside fellow advertising executive Harry, played by Humphrey Bogart. Jimmy returns to the city alone and throws himself into his work, turning into the driven man Linda always wanted him to be. As Harry makes his feelings for Linda clear, Linda realizes she’ll have to chose between Harry and Jimmy.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Let’s get this out of the way: there is one, and only one, reason to endure Men Are Such Fools: to see Humphrey Bogart look utterly ridiculous in his unitard swimsuit. A fast-forward button can make this a much more pleasant endeavor, as the rest of the film is awful. Neither of the leads is likable. Lane starts out okay, but as soon as Morris makes his entrance, she goes downhill. You see, Morris&amp;#39; character is a total ass. He bullies Lane’s character at every turn, sabotages her career, and disregards her hopes and dreams. Thus, when Lane’s character suddenly goes giddy and agrees to marry him, you can’t help but lose any sympathy for her. Things get better–briefly–when Bogart shows up. You’re practically screaming at Lane to go for him, but instead she only uses him to get back with the lunky Morris. Despite the title, the film makes it pretty clear that it’s the women, not men who are the fools. Was this really how it worked in 1938?&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>
      3. Black Legion (1937) ★★½☆☆
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/black-legion-1937' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/black-legion-1937</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;Bogart plays Frank Taylor, a senior machinist and family man in line for a rich promotion to foreman. When he’s passed over in favor of a younger coworker named Dombrowski, Frank falls in with the titular Legion, a black-robed hate group who runs Dombrowski out of town. Frank ascends to foreman, and for a short while things are great, but after Frank’s Legion-mandated recruiting activities lead to an accident at the shop, Frank is demoted in favor of his neighbor. Once again, the Legion come to Frank’s aid, but the secrecy and violence begin to wear on Frank who takes to drinking heavily, leading to the departure of his wife, along with their young son. Alone and despondent, a drunken Frank confesses everything to his longtime friend Ed, but panics the next morning and tells local Legion head Cliff what he’s done. Cliff cooks up a rumor about Ed in order to rile up the Legion, who kidnap Ed, but things don’t go as planned, leaving Frank with blood on his hands and nowhere to turn.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Bogart shines in what should have been a break-out role, and the script’s multi-faceted depiction of the Legion is enlightening, from the radio demagogues cultivating resentment and fear all the way to the profiteers behind the scenes, cashing in on the sales of Legion uniforms and revolvers. But Frank’s going from honest family-man to drunken womanizer in what seems like a matter of weeks gives the film a trite, after-school-special feel that undermines the still-relevant social context.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>
      2. Thief (1981) ★★★★☆
    </title>
    <link href='http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/reviews/thief-1981' />
    <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://movielog.frankshowalter.com/thief-1981</id>
    <content type='html'>
      &lt;p&gt;Caan plays Frank, a Chicago-based professional safe cracker looking to retire and start a family with his new girlfriend, played by Weld. Needing one last big score to secure his financial future, Frank agrees to go to work for Leo, a powerful crime boss, who sets up a high-dollar diamond heist in LA. Frank and his crew take down the score, but when Leo reneges on their deal it sets up a violent confrontation between Frank and Leo’s crew. Michael Mann’s first film is effective, stylish thriller peppered with great performances and a very satisfying third act. It’s a slicker–but no less resonant–version of the kind of movie Sam Peckinpah might have made with Steve McQueen.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
