<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?><feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'><title>Frank's Movie Log</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/feed.xml' rel='self' /><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com' /><updated>2015-02-09T20:07:10-05:00</updated><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com</id><author><name>Frank Showalter</name></author><entry><title>30. Curse of the Crimson Altar (1968) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/curse-of-the-crimson-altar-1968/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/curse-of-the-crimson-altar-1968</id><updated>2015-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Curse of the Crimson Altar&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;The Crimson Cult&lt;/em&gt; here in the USA) can&amp;#39;t decide how seriously it wants to take itself. This is evident from the opening scene. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A droning noise whines in and out as a young man named Peter Manning stands wearing a suit. He looks dazed. In front of him, a nude woman suffers a whip while lying strapped to a table. Men in black robes look on. One has a goat. Wearing a large headdress complete with ram horns, a green-skinned Barbra Steel introduces herself as Lavinia, the &amp;quot;Keeper of the Black Secret”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. She asks if Peter knows why he&amp;#39;s there. He does. She asks if he&amp;#39;s ready to sign. He is. A man brings over a large book and Peter signs his name. Then Lavinia hands Peter a dagger. Peter stabs the girl on the table without a moment&amp;#39;s hesitation. There&amp;#39;s a quick-cut to the goat, which seems distressed. Lavinia snaps her fingers. There&amp;#39;s a crack of thunder. A muscular man dressed in a leather bikini bottom, leather arm-bands, and a studded leather cap with antlers brings over a branding iron which he presses into Peter&amp;#39;s chest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, that happens. The film packs a few more of these trippy, S&amp;amp;M-tinged sequences, but they exist more-or-less outside the main narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story concerns Peter&amp;#39;s brother, Robert, played by Mark Eden. When Peter doesn&amp;#39;t return home, Robert goes looking for him at his last known location, a remote country estate called Craxton Lodge. Robert&amp;#39;s arrival coincides with a local festival celebrating the burning of the witch Lavinia some three hundred years earlier. The estate’s owner, J.D. Morely, played by Christopher Lee, claims to have never heard of Peter, but invites Robert to stay on to continue his search. Robert agrees. Robert also meets another of the locals, Professor Marsh, played by Boris Karloff. Marsh, conveniently, is an expert on witchcraft. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the film unwinds, the tone veers between cult conspiracy and Scooby-Doo mystery. Robert discovers secret doors and a fake spiderweb machine en-route to learning the truth behind his brother’s disappearance. But by the time the credits roll we&amp;#39;re left wondering if the scenes with Lavinia were meant to be real or imagined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes ambiguity helps a film resonate. This just feels like the filmmakers were too cool for school and found the horror elements a bit contemptuous. Consider the poor attempt at meta-humor. When one of the characters compares Craxton Lodge to “one of those old houses in horror films,” Robert replies, “It’s like Boris Karloff’s going to pop up at any moment.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first viewing of &lt;em&gt;The Curse of the Crimson Altar&lt;/em&gt; , I considered it something of a guilty pleasure. The over-the-top dream sequences and gratuitous nudity were good for a chuckle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But watching it a second time, I found the film far less entertaining. Sure, Karloff is great. Even wheelchair-bound at eighty-years-old, he could still command a scene. But that’s about all this movie has going for it. Lee’s role gives him little to do, and Barbara Steele is wasted. The story’s mystery elements, already weak on the first viewing, border on tedious the second time around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that this was one of Karloff’s final films, it’s probably required viewing for any serious fan of classic horror. Just don&amp;#39;t watch it a second time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record, there is no &lt;em&gt;Crimson&lt;/em&gt; Altar or &lt;em&gt;Crimson&lt;/em&gt; Cult. &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>29. The Town That Dreaded Sundown (2014) ★★★☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-town-that-dreaded-sundown-2014/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-town-that-dreaded-sundown-2014</id><updated>2015-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown&lt;/em&gt; starts with a prologue recounting a series of unsolved murders that occurred in Texarkana in 1946. It talks about how those killings formed the basis for the original film, &lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown (1976)&lt;/em&gt;, which screens every Halloween somewhere in Texarkana. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film opens on one of those screenings. It&amp;#39;s a drive-in. The camera pans down to a teen couple sitting on the hood of a car. He seems into the film, but she looks uneasy. She says it’s not her kind of movie. He asks her if she wants to go. She does, and they head out. As they leave, the camera picks up a preacher imploring the patrons to remember that people really died back in 1946.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The couple head out for a quiet, deserted area where they can be alone. He makes small talk as they drive. The camera shows them at a tilted angle. It&amp;#39;s an on-the-nose gimmick that foreshadows one of the film&amp;#39;s biggest weaknesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon they&amp;#39;re parked. They start kissing, but the girl spots a man in the nearby woods. He&amp;#39;s dressed just like the killer from the movie. But this is no prank. The man breaks the car&amp;#39;s window with the butt of a revolver. He orders them out of the car at gunpoint, then forces the girl to turn around while he stabs the boy to death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we&amp;#39;re off and running. By genre definitions, the film is a slasher, but I&amp;#39;m always hesitant to use that term. For many people, that equates to the &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; series of films, which were, for the most part, more monster and survival-horror films than slasher. &lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown&lt;/em&gt; is more of a violent mystery. Victims are stalked and murdered in a brutal but stylish manner and we work along with the protagonist to deduce the killer&amp;#39;s identity from a number of suspects. To that end, &lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown&lt;/em&gt; may be the first rural giallo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a lot to like. The supporting cast includes Edward Herrmann as the aforementioned preacher, and Gary Cole as a sheriff’s deputy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script’s meta-sequel approach works well. It avoids the trap of aggrandizing the original film by regulating it to well-researched pulp entertainment. Granted, this film does play as something of a remake, but by excising the original’s head-scratching bits of comic relief, this entry crafts a much taunter narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the film is far from perfect. Remember the gimmick shot I mentioned earlier? The movie is full of them. Some of them work, but their impact is lost in the shuffle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the scene, set at night, where a woman flees the killer into a huge wheat field. The killer has a gun. He fires and she drops to the ground amid the wheat. He approaches, but can’t find the body. Cut to a bird’s eye shot of the field and we see the woman crawling away from the killer as he stalks forward. They’re not more than six feet apart, but they can’t see each other. The shot’s only held for a few moments before we cut back to a tight shot of the killer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? That was a great shot. Keep it. Cut the music. Just give us the sound of the wind and let us watch from above as she crawls, hoping against hope that he doesn’t see her. Their meeting is inevitable, but the tension would have been palpable watching the two skew towards one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the ending. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we get to that, let me say that I liked the movie. The location photography, colorful supporting cast, and competent script make for a solid little slasher. So, having said that, and having given you a sense of what the film is about and what it’s like, I feel my job as reviewer is done. If you want to stop reading here, I’ll understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still with me? Okay. I didn’t love the ending. I didn’t hate it either, but I did feel like it felt like a missed opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why. The script touches on the notion of violence inspired by the media several times, but only in passing. I felt like the film was really building to something however, and when the heroine makes to leave town with her grandmother, it struck me. What if this is the end of the movie? She leaves, the killer is never caught. All the bits about inspired violence coalesce into a biting commentary. The killer will be there as long as he has an audience. It would even dovetail nicely with the original&amp;#39;s ambiguous ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, some folks would hate it, but I bet a lot of theater-goers hated the original’s ending too. And yet, that ending helped the original resonate enough to inspire a remake almost forty years later.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>28. The Big Steal (1949) ★★★★☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-big-steal-1949/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-big-steal-1949</id><updated>2015-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Like any good script, &lt;em&gt;The Big Steal&lt;/em&gt; starts as late into the story as possible. Aboard an ocean liner that&amp;#39;s just docked in Veracruz, Mexico, William Bendix bursts into Robert Mitchum&amp;#39;s cabin holding a gun. He&amp;#39;s after something he believes Mitchum stole. Mitchum says he doesn&amp;#39;t have it. “You’ve got the wrong man,” Mitchum says. Bendix isn’t buying it. He moves to arrest Mitchum. Mitchum overpowers Bendix, knocking him out. Mitchum takes Bendix&amp;#39;s gun and identification. The identification reads: Captain Vincent Blake of the US Army. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After debarking, Mitchum crosses paths with Jane Greer. It&amp;#39;s a short meeting, as Mitchum has to duck out of sight as Bendix emerges from the ship. Once the coast is clear, Mitchum tries to catch a cab, only to find Greer has gotten the last one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cut to a room inside the Hotel Mexico. We see Patric Knowles packing. He’s in a rush. His eyes are darting around. There&amp;#39;s a knock at the door. Knowles pulls a gun and moves to the side of the door, ready to plug whoever comes in. Then we hear Greer&amp;#39;s voice, telling him to open up. We learn that Knowles is Greer&amp;#39;s fiancee. But she&amp;#39;s not there to marry him, she&amp;#39;s there because he ran off with her savings, about two thousand dollars. She wants it back. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowles tries to sweet talk her, but Greer cuts him off saying, &amp;quot;The last time you did that it cost me my bank account.&amp;quot; Knowles tries to make her feel bad for harping on him about the money saying, &amp;quot;There&amp;#39;s that dollar sign again.&amp;quot; But Greer snaps back, &amp;quot;Where? I don&amp;#39;t see it. Come on, hand it over.&amp;quot; Then, dripping with sarcasm, &amp;quot;I was saving that money for my trousseau.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowles gives Greer the slip, and a few beats later we learn that Mitchum is after Knowles too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the film is set. It’s one big chase. Bendix chases Mitchum who, along with Greer, chases Knowles. Mitchum and Greer form an uneasy partnership as they travel across the Mexican countryside from Veracruz to Tehuacán&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  As the story unfolds we learn what was stolen, and who did the stealing. Mitchum and Greer warm to each other. Everything culminates in a surprising, but satisfying finale. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On paper, it&amp;#39;s another forgettable lower-budget entry from RKO, the once premier studio that had fallen to disarray under Howard Hughes. But thanks to a crackerjack script, &lt;em&gt;The Big Steal&lt;/em&gt; is better than it probably had any right to be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script is a thing of beauty. Consider how little information we&amp;#39;re given as the movie begins. Rather than open with a flashback or exposition, we’re thrown right into one unnamed man confronting another over an event we know nothing about. That’s great storytelling. But it’s when Greer confronts Knowles that the script really sparkles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s refreshing to see such an independent female character. She&amp;#39;s self assured without being arrogant. Insistent without being whiny. The script may leave the fisticuffs to the male characters, but Greer&amp;#39;s character holds her own in the numerous bouts of verbal sparring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script also does a great job of subverting our expectations. From the anything-but-inept Mexican police inspector, to Greer—not Mitchum—being the one to get them out of various jams, the script defies the genre’s conventions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And topping it all off, there&amp;#39;s a nice touch where Mitchum actually wears some of the results of his tussles. From a bloody nose to a beaten face, the film’s fights have visible consequences. Something all too rare in Hollywood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, it&amp;#39;s not a perfect film. The extended car chase feels tacked on and forced. And Knowles and Bendix don&amp;#39;t quite hold their own against Mitchum and Greer in terms of star wattage. But really, these are weaknesses instead of faults. &lt;em&gt;The Big Steal&lt;/em&gt; takes a B-movie plot and elevates it to near greatness thanks to a well-crafted script peppered with crackling dialog. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They actually shot in Mexico, which helps to belie the film’s modest budget.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>27. Rasputin: The Mad Monk (1966) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/rasputin-the-mad-monk-1966/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/rasputin-the-mad-monk-1966</id><updated>2015-01-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rasputin: The Mad Monk&lt;/em&gt; opens with Rasputin, played by Christopher Lee, arriving at an inn and demanding wine. When he&amp;#39;s told the innkeeper is unavailable due to his ill wife, an annoyed Rasputin marches upstairs. He storms into the bedroom, and proceeds to &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; the disease out of the frail woman, drawing it into his now red-hot hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dancing and merriment follow. Rasputin gets good and drunk and takes the innkeeper&amp;#39;s daughter out to the barn. This doesn&amp;#39;t sit well with her young suitor who brawls with Rasputin. Rasputin chops the young lad&amp;#39;s hand off saying, &amp;quot;He won&amp;#39;t trouble us anymore,&amp;quot; then makes to get back with the daughter. But the wounded suitor brings the rest of the village, who chase Rasputin out of town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great introduction. If only the rest of the film lived up to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the story unfolds, Rasputin travels to Saint Petersburg. There he insinuates himself into the Tsaritsa&amp;#39;s court by hypnotizing one of her ladies-in-waiting. Barbara Shelley plays the lady in question. There&amp;#39;s a good bit where Rasputin, having just hypnotized Shelley&amp;#39;s character into sleeping with him, tells her to leave some money on the dresser. As Rasputin&amp;#39;s influence grows, members of the court begin to conspire against him. There&amp;#39;s an overly elaborate plot involving poison, some grappling, then it&amp;#39;s all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a terrific performance by Lee, and Hammer&amp;#39;s solid production values&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the film underwhelms. It treats the character of Rasputin as a one-dimensional monster. This wouldn’t be so bad, but the talky script vacillates between biographical drama and horror without committing to either.  The result? Rasputin spends too much time drinking and dancing and not enough time chopping off hands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, they spliced in a ballroom shot from &lt;em&gt;Anastasia (1956)&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>26. The Devil Rides Out (1968) ★★★★☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-devil-rides-out-1968/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-devil-rides-out-1968</id><updated>2015-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Some films have no business working as well as they do. &lt;em&gt;The Devil Rides Out&lt;/em&gt; is one such film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set in 1929, the story opens with the dashing Duke de Richleau awaiting the arrival of his good friend, Rex Van Ryn. The Duke is played by Hammer stalwart Christopher Lee who, in a rare change of pace, gets to play the hero and does a fine job of it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rex arrives piloting his own biplane, which is the extent of the characterization the script allots him.  After landing, he and the Duke set out to call on their young friend, Simon. What they find upon arriving at Simon&amp;#39;s palatial house alarms the Duke. It seems Simon has fallen in with a group of Satanists led by the sinister Mocata, played by Charles Gray. As the Duke says, “Simon is playing the most dangerous game known to mankind.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lee’s dialog is full of lines like that. They should induce groans, but Lee pulls them off with flair. He opens the commentary track on the DVD saying that he’s largely responsible for the film being made. He was a big fan of the novel by Dennis Wheatley and brought the book to the attention of studio executives. His performance is reminiscent of Peter Cushing’s turn as Van Helsing in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews/horror-of-dracula-1958/&quot;&gt;Horror of Dracula (1958)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and his admiration of the source material shines through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opposite Lee, Gray delivers a smooth, understated performance that’s almost as magnetic as Lee&amp;#39;s&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Consider the scene where he calls on the Duke&amp;#39;s niece in an attempt to extract Simon. She makes to throw him out, but he leaves of his own accord saying, “I&amp;#39;m leaving. I shall not be back. But something will.” He pauses for a moment then adds, “Tonight. Something will come for Simon and the girl.” His tone is casual, not threatening, and all the more menacing for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the supernatural elements, &lt;em&gt;The Devil Rides Out&lt;/em&gt;  isn’t really a horror movie at all&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It’s a terrific pulp adventure. Sure, the characters are archetypes, and the stilted dialog may induce a wry smirk, but the film rolls along at such a good clip, we’ve hardly a moment to care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gray had just starred in &lt;em&gt;You Only Live Twice (1967)&lt;/em&gt; but Hammer&amp;#39;s first choice for Mocata was another Bond alumnus: Gert Fröbe, Goldfinger himself!&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fearing moviegoers would think &lt;em&gt;The Devil Rides Out&lt;/em&gt; was a western, Twentieth Century Fox changed the title to &lt;em&gt;The Devil&amp;#39;s Bride&lt;/em&gt; for the USA theatrical release.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>25. The One I Love (2014) ★★★★☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-one-i-love-2014/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-one-i-love-2014</id><updated>2015-01-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Warning: There be spoilers here. It&amp;#39;s not possible to talk about &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; in a meaningful way without them. But it’s a movie best seen with an open mind. So I encourage you, if you haven&amp;#39;t seen it, to do so. It&amp;#39;s not perfect, but the first two acts are brilliant and it&amp;#39;s original enough to warrant a look. Go ahead, I&amp;#39;ll wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back? Okay, here we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Duplass and Elisabeth Moss play Ethan and Sophie, a young couple on the brink of divorce. They&amp;#39;ve drifted apart. Their counselor sends them to a remote retreat for a weekend getaway. He believes it’s just what they need to reconnect and rediscover one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The retreat turns out to be a sizable country estate, complete with pool and guest house. Ethan and Sophie arrive and discover they&amp;#39;re the only people present. They settle in, have a nice dinner, and smoke some marijuana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sophie wanders over to the guest house.  Ethan joins her. They laugh, talk and have a wonderful time. The best they&amp;#39;ve had in years. They have sex. Later, Sophie heads back to the main house to grab some things. Inside, she&amp;#39;s surprised to find Ethan lying on the couch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She laughs and asks how he&amp;#39;s beaten her back. Ethan looks confused. He&amp;#39;s just woken up. Sophie stops laughing. She asks him why he&amp;#39;s acting like this after they just has sex. Ethan looks at her with bewilderment. He tells her he&amp;#39;s been asleep on the couch since they smoked the marijuana. Sophie storms off, furious at Ethan&amp;#39;s unfunny joke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethan wanders over to the guest house and falls asleep on the couch there. In the middle of the night, Sophie joins him. They snuggle. Ethan wakes to find Sophie making breakfast. Including bacon. Sophie hates bacon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to this point, the film has cultivated a subtle aura of menace. The long shadow-filled shots of Sophie walking back to the house and through the empty kitchen wouldn&amp;#39;t seem out of place in a home invasion thriller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now we&amp;#39;ve got an inkling of what&amp;#39;s going on, and to the film&amp;#39;s credit, it doesn&amp;#39;t drag things out.  Ethan and Sophie soon realize that when one of them enters the guest house alone, they&amp;#39;re greeted by a doppelgänger of the other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They run. Again, credit to the film. It&amp;#39;s what most folks would do. But then Ethan and Sophie get to thinking about it. Especially Sophie. They talk. The film&amp;#39;s tone shifts from menacing to quirky. Sophie suggests going back. Weren&amp;#39;t they there to try new things? Ethan agrees. They return to the retreat and set some ground rules for the guest house. Fifteen minute sessions, no intimate activity. Total honesty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, these rules soon go out the window. Sophie begins sneaking out to see the other Ethan. Ethan ends up impersonating his doppelgänger in order to sleep with Sophie. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, Ethan gets some voicemails from friends and family members. The messages suggest that Ethan made a series of calls in the middle of the night asking random questions about his past. Some of his clothes seem to have gone missing as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon the doppelgängers confront Ethan and Sophie as a couple. The four try to have a nice dinner, but Ethan&amp;#39;s suspicion and resentment bubble over. He storms off to the guest house. Once inside, he finds he can&amp;#39;t get out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In time, Sophie&amp;#39;s doppelgänger arrives. Then the film falls apart. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to this point, the doppelgängers felt like a novel device the script employed to visualize Ethan and Sophie&amp;#39;s perceptions of one another. This sort of thing could feel like a gimmick and veer into into cheesy fantasy, but the film stays grounded by focusing on the harsh realities of trying to make a relationship work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end, the doppelgängers require no explanation. They exist to serve the story. The film even floats this notion, suggesting that some things “Just happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the movie isn&amp;#39;t confident enough to leave it at that. And so Sophie&amp;#39;s doppelgänger reveals the truth to Ethan. Her and Doppelgänger Ethan were another couple sent to the retreat like Ethan and Sophie, but now they&amp;#39;re trapped. The only way they can leave is to break up Ethan and Sophie so they can take their place. But something&amp;#39;s gone wrong. The other Ethan has fallen in love with the real Sophie. He&amp;#39;s planning to leave with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that wealth of exposition, the plot kicks in. Doppelgänger Sophie lets Ethan out of the guest house and distracts Doppelgänger Ethan (by posing as the real Sophie) so that Ethan can warn Sophie. When Sophie refuses to leave with him, Doppelgänger Ethan tries leaving by himself. An invisible wall knocks him cold. Ethan and Sophie leave. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next we see, they&amp;#39;re lying in bed giggling. Sophie gets up and offers to make breakfast, asking if Ethan wants bacon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film name-drops &lt;em&gt;The Twilight Zone&lt;/em&gt; but the first two acts are more reminiscent of David Lynch&amp;#39;s work.  Like Lynch&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Lost Highway (1997)&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mulholland Dr. (1999)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; explores the subject of identity through a strange, inexplicable event. But the difference is that in Lynch&amp;#39;s films, the character&amp;#39;s motivations are never explicitly verbalized. If you define them, the rest of the story must serve them. When it doesn’t, you have plot holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And boy does &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; have a lot of them. The whole film does&amp;#39;t make any sense, really. What was the point of imprisoning couples there? Why transform the previous couples into doppelgängers of the next ones? Why can they only leave after the other two have broken up? Why did their therapist send them in the first place? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all this, &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; impressed me. It&amp;#39;s a brilliant concept that&amp;#39;s handled with the perfect tone. That it goes off the rails at the end doesn&amp;#39;t detract from the great performances and it&amp;#39;s biting insight into relationships. The plot holes don’t ruin the movie, they just handicap it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, just imagine if it didn&amp;#39;t try to explain the doppelgängers. Imagine if the scene where Ethan hears the other couple&amp;#39;s voices turning into his and Sophie&amp;#39;s was left out. Imagine if when Ethan confronted doppelgänger Sophie about not being real, she just sat and stared at him with that slightly unnatural smile. Then cut to the scene of Ethan and Sophie back home in bed laughing and Sophie getting up to make breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose this ending would leave some portion of the audience wanting. Lynch’s films are famous for that. They’re like lego sets. They provide the audience with the building blocks of a story, but leave it to the viewer to create their own interpretation and meaning. Unfortunately, &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; is less like a set of legos and more like a puzzle. One that&amp;#39;s missing a few pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>24. The Angry Hills (1959) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-angry-hills-1959/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-angry-hills-1959</id><updated>2015-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Angry Hills&lt;/em&gt; starts well enough. It&amp;#39;s 1941. Robert Mitchum plays Mike Morrison, an American Correspondent who has just arrived in Greece. The Nazis are preparing to take the country and Mike plans to be on the next plane out. A member of the Greek resistance presents Mike with a list of Nazi collaborators. He urges Mike to take the list to British Intelligence. Mike declines, saying he doesn’t want to get involved. Later, while out with a friend, Mike discovers the list in his jacket.  Mike attempts to unload the list to another Greek agent, but Gestapo agents are already on Mike&amp;#39;s tail. They force him to flee through the darkened back streets of Athens. Mike escapes by hitching a ride on a British convoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, so good. But then the film goes off the rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script jumps ahead. We learn that the Germans bombed the British Convoy and that Mike survived thanks to some fishermen who took him to a remote village. &lt;em&gt;Then&lt;/em&gt; the film jumps back and we see the convoy get bombed. Then we&amp;#39;re back with Mike in a small Greek village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These village scenes are dull and uninspiring. Stilted melodrama replaces suspense. A young, hotheaded female villager named Eleftheria nurses Mike back to health. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Mike is healthy, the film devolves into a clumsy wartime adventure. The villagers ask Mike to lead them on a raid of a Nazi supply depot. Because, who better to lead a guerrilla raid in the Greek countryside than an American journalist? While they&amp;#39;re planning the raid, a British soldier shows up, says he&amp;#39;d like to help, learns all the details about the raid, then leaves. No one is concerned. Of course, the raid goes bad. The Nazi&amp;#39;s slaughter all the men save Mike and another, who manage to get away. When they can&amp;#39;t understand what happened, we almost laugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a bit, Mike and Eleftheria travel to a convent where Mike&amp;#39;s given passage back to Athens. Once there, things get a little better, as the film shifts again, this time to a heist picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa, a widowed British spy, is Mike&amp;#39;s contact in Athens. The Gestapo gets wind of this and kidnaps Lisa&amp;#39;s children. She&amp;#39;s to turn over Mike if she wants to see her kids again. She sets Mike up, but changes her mind at the last minute. To rescue her children, she makes a deal with a local underworld figure named Chesney, played by Sebastian Cabot. Chesney double crosses the local Nazi agents while Lisa distracts the chief officer. It&amp;#39;s a satisfactory ending, but one in which Mike is superfluous. By this point the list is all but forgotten, having been supplanted by Lisa&amp;#39;s children as the motivating factor. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a lot of good here. The film looks great, especially when it&amp;#39;s in Athens. The location photography, and rich use of shadows give it a terrific sense of atmosphere. The cast is solid too. Mitchum is great as a reluctant hero. Stanley Baker is even better as the Gestapo Agent charged with capturing Mitchum. Cap it off with Sebastian Cabot channeling Sidney Greenstreet in the best way possible and this should have been a good movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the end, &lt;em&gt;The Angry Hills&lt;/em&gt; isn&amp;#39;t really a movie at all.  It starts as a Hitchcockian spy thriller. But before it can get going, it drops that premise and sets up an action picture. And before &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; can pay off, it tries out a heist picture. Had it followed through on any of these premises, it would likely have turned out better&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Instead where given the beginning of one movie, the middle of another, and the end of yet another. Quite a disappointment given the talent involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, maybe not the wartime action premise. That was just silly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>23. Rachel and the Stranger (1948) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/rachel-and-the-stranger-1948/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/rachel-and-the-stranger-1948</id><updated>2015-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Rachel and the Stranger&lt;/em&gt;, William Holden plays David Harvey. David is a pioneer farmer living with his young son Davey in the Ohio wilderness. David&amp;#39;s wife Susan died the previous year, sinking him into depression. It&amp;#39;s only after finding Davey using a page from one of his school books as a sail for a toy boat, that David resolves to find a new wife. Not for love, but because he knew how important it was to Susan that Davey not grow up &amp;quot;woodsy&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David travels to the nearby stockade and consults the Parson. The Parson suggests David buy the contract of a bond woman named Rachael. David likes the idea of a servant. A woman but not a wife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Parson says, &amp;quot;Decent church folk don&amp;#39;t live together, man and woman, under the same roof without marriage.&amp;quot; So David marries Rachael and takes her back to his farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though he is distant, David is not cruel to her. She sleeps in the bed, David sleeps in another room on the floor. Rachael is timid, but works to endear herself. David takes no notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davey, however, is downright cruel. When she tells him she was brought there to give him his schooling and sort of mother him, Davey spits back, &amp;quot;The devil it was! You&amp;#39;re a bond slave is all!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things change when Jim, a family friend played by Robert Mitchum, arrives. Jim&amp;#39;s a hunter and tracker. He was a one time suitor of Susan, and both he and David were surprised she chose David over him. Jim, it seems, has decided to settle down, and takes an instant interest in Rachel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jim is attentive and charming. David gets jealous. Both men begin to vie for Rachel’s attention, culminating in a fist-fight that leads to Rachel leaving them both. They go after her. There&amp;#39;s an obligatory Indian attack, then it&amp;#39;s over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three leads are solid. Young and Holden are convincing, and Mitchum is great as a laconic woodsman. But this is not a good movie. It takes us for simpletons incapable of picking up any subtlety. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider when, after arriving in the cabin, Rachael is clearing the table. David and Davey are talking. Davey says he won&amp;#39;t be getting any music lessons. We see Rachael pause. This should have been it. Instead, the film cuts to a drawn-out close-up of Rachael. We see her look off screen, open her mouth to say something, then close it and look down at Davey. Davey looks back, daring her to talk. She doesn&amp;#39;t and walks away. It&amp;#39;s a ten second scene that should have played out in an instant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script is clumsy too. Consider the scene where David and Davey are out working. They hear a turkey call. Davey whines abut wanting to go take a shot at the bird. David grabs Davey and dives to the ground. The turkey call is the signal of the Shawnee Indians, he says. Of course, it&amp;#39;s just Jim, but when he steps out of the woods to greet David he tells them there&amp;#39;s signs of Shawnee up to the north. We haven&amp;#39;t heard a thing about Indians up to this point, but now the script mentions Shawnee four times in the span of two minutes. There isn&amp;#39;t a mention of them again until they attack in the finale. This scene, like the Indian attack itself, feels tacked-on and forced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that&amp;#39;s how most of this film works. Characters don&amp;#39;t act organically, they act &lt;em&gt;conveniently&lt;/em&gt;. Rachael is a reserved mouse until Jim and David get into a fight, then she announces she&amp;#39;s leaving. Rachael has to leave so that David can win her back. Davey spends most of the film spitting venom at Rachael, but after she makes him a meal one night, he&amp;#39;s happy to have her as his mother. Davey has to like her to allow David to fall in love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And speaking of Davey, he&amp;#39;s an awful character. He&amp;#39;s whiny and obstinate. We&amp;#39;re given no reason to like him. Yes, he misses his mother. But the way he&amp;#39;s presented, one suspects he was annoying long before Susan departed this earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a kernel of a good story here, and the three leads are more than capable of pulling it off. But the hackneyed melodramatic fable they&amp;#39;re given to work with is frustrating at best, and annoying at worst. The adult themes of intimacy and emotional neglect belie a trite narrative that&amp;#39;s presented in a ham-handed and condescending manner. Given the talent involved, we deserve better.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>22. Locke (2013) ★★★★☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/locke-2013/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/locke-2013</id><updated>2015-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Locke&lt;/em&gt; is not a great film, but it is a good one. If you&amp;#39;re on the fence about seeing it, do so. Don&amp;#39;t read any further, as we&amp;#39;re going to talk about plot and this movie works best the less you know going in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still here? Okay, here we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Locke&lt;/em&gt; opens with a wide shot of a construction site. It&amp;#39;s dark. Spotlights illuminate a massive foundation hole. Early the next morning, they will pour the concrete. It will be the largest commercial pour in Europe. Ivan Locke (Tom Hardy) is the construction manager in charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ivan gets into his car. He pulls away from the curb and makes a call. He gets a woman&amp;#39;s voicemail. He tells her he&amp;#39;s gotten her message and that he&amp;#39;s on his way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the film unfolds we learn that Ivan is traveling to London from Birmingham. We also learn the circumstances surrounding the trip. Last year he had a one night stand while away on a job. The first and only time he&amp;#39;s strayed in fifteen years of marriage. But the woman, Bethan, became pregnant. Now, the baby has come early and she&amp;#39;s gone into labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the film happens in near real-time, as Ivan juggles a series of calls. We learn more about him. He is both diligent and pragmatic. The kind of man who makes checklists but is able to adapt to unforeseen circumstances. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so it is with a deliberate logic that he approaches his current situation. He has fathered a child. Now he must do right by it. A deep-rooted psychological need drives him. Ivan&amp;#39;s father abandoned him. Ivan refuses to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film doles out this information in small bits as it unfolds. Each nugget raises the emotional stakes and increases the story’s tension. In time, Ivan loses his job, his family and his home. He accepts these events with a calm detachment. These are the consequences of his actions. He compartmentalizes them. He holds to his logic. He must be there for his child. Early on, when Bethan asks if he loves her, Ivan replies &amp;quot;How can I? I don&amp;#39;t know you.&amp;quot; His tone is not cruel. It is the voice of a man trying to convince her of a truth he needs to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching Ivan’s world unravel is a compelling journey. Tom Hardy holds our attention from the very first scene. We want to learn more about his character. Through his eyes and inflection, Hardy conveys a character struggling to contain a sea of emotions. Setting the entire film in Ivan’s car doesn’t feel like a stunt, it feels natural. It adds to the claustrophobic sense of desperation that the film cultivates. By the end, we’re hanging on every word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But about that end. Just as abruptly as it began, the film is over. Ivan&amp;#39;s world has changed and he heads off to what will be, for him, a new life. I didn&amp;#39;t like this ending, but I&amp;#39;m not sure how I would change it. It felt anti-climatic. Not enough to ruin the film, but enough that it left me wanting. But perhaps that&amp;#39;s the point. Just like Ivan, we’re left with an odd sense of detachment.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>21. She Couldn't Say No (1954) ★★★☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/she-couldnt-say-no-1954/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/she-couldnt-say-no-1954</id><updated>2015-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Had it dared to be as provocative as it&amp;#39;s title, &lt;em&gt;She Couldn&amp;#39;t Say No&lt;/em&gt; might have been something special. As is, it’s not a bad film, but it is something of a let-down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story follows an oil heiress named Korby Lane, played by Jean Simmons. Korby travels to the small town of Progress in rural Arkansas. Once there, she begins anonymously doling out large sums of money to the townsfolk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also takes an interest in Doc Sellers, played by Robert Mitchum. Doc susses out Korby&amp;#39;s motivations, and tries to dissuade her. But Korby is stubborn. Her generosity backfires. Flush with cash, the town vet pulls up stakes, leaving the local farmers in a lurch. So does the owner of the boarding house where Korby&amp;#39;s been staying. The town drunk, played by the always charming Arthur Hunnicutt, almost dies of alcohol poisoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the town descends into chaos, Korby realizes the error of her ways. She comes clean as the town&amp;#39;s beneficiary and says there&amp;#39;ll be no more money. Korby and Doc get together and we&amp;#39;re led to believe the town is more-or-less back to normal. Of course, we know that can&amp;#39;t be true, but this is part of how the film lets us down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a film built on a solid premise with a good cast. But the script has no edge. It plays like a bucolic romantic comedy. Nothing serious happens until the end, when masses of people show up at the general store. They&amp;#39;re all from out of town, hoping to register a local address to get a piece of the pie. The crowd swells. Tempers run short. Someone has a gun. Things start to turn ugly, but Doc arrives in time to settle things down with a hearty speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if he didn&amp;#39;t? What if the film started as a comedy but then subverted the genre to show the underside of small town life? A biting satire that &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; explored the effects of sudden wealth on rural America. It might be wrong to criticize the film based on what &lt;em&gt;wasn&amp;#39;t&lt;/em&gt; made, but storytelling is about making decisions. And a decision &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to do something is still a decision.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>