<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?><feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'><title>Frank's Movie Log</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/feed.xml' rel='self' /><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com' /><updated>2015-01-10T20:53:42-05:00</updated><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com</id><author><name>Frank Showalter</name></author><entry><title>21. She Couldn't Say No (1954) ★★★☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/she-couldnt-say-no-1954/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/she-couldnt-say-no-1954</id><updated>2015-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Had it dared to be as provocative as it&amp;#39;s title, &lt;em&gt;She Couldn&amp;#39;t Say No&lt;/em&gt; might have been something special. As is, it’s not a bad film, but it is something of a let-down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story follows an oil heiress named Korby Lane, played by Jean Simmons. Korby travels to the small town of Progress in rural Arkansas. Once there, she begins anonymously doling out large sums of money to the townsfolk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also takes an interest in Doc Sellers, played by Robert Mitchum. Doc susses out Korby&amp;#39;s motivations, and tries to dissuade her. But Korby is stubborn. Her generosity backfires. Flush with cash, the town vet pulls up stakes, leaving the local farmers in a lurch. So does the owner of the boarding house where Korby&amp;#39;s been staying. The town drunk, played by the always charming Arthur Hunnicutt, almost dies of alcohol poisoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the town descends into chaos, Korby realizes the error of her ways. She comes clean as the town&amp;#39;s beneficiary and says there&amp;#39;ll be no more money. Korby and Doc get together and we&amp;#39;re led to believe the town is more-or-less back to normal. Of course, we know that can&amp;#39;t be true, but this is part of how the film lets us down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a film built on a solid premise with a good cast. But the script has no edge. It plays like a bucolic romantic comedy. Nothing serious happens until the end, when masses of people show up at the general store. They&amp;#39;re all from out of town, hoping to register a local address to get a piece of the pie. The crowd swells. Tempers run short. Someone has a gun. Things start to turn ugly, but Doc arrives in time to settle things down with a hearty speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if he didn&amp;#39;t? What if the film started as a comedy but then subverted the genre to show the underside of small town life? A biting satire that &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; explored the effects of sudden wealth on rural America. It might be wrong to criticize the film based on what &lt;em&gt;wasn&amp;#39;t&lt;/em&gt; made, but storytelling is about making decisions. And a decision &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to do something is still a decision.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>20. Friday the 13th Part VIII: Jason Takes Manhattan (1989) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/friday-the-13th-part-viii-jason-takes-manhattan-1989/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/friday-the-13th-part-viii-jason-takes-manhattan-1989</id><updated>2015-01-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;I was about to start high school when this movie came out. I was too young to see it, not that I wanted to. It was the eighth entry in what had become a disregarded franchise. Slasher films were passé.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all that, I remember this movie&amp;#39;s release. This was well before the internet was a household thing, but that didn&amp;#39;t stop the news from spreading. In a film called &lt;em&gt;Jason Takes Manhattan&lt;/em&gt;, Jason didn&amp;#39;t actually get to New York until the last twenty minutes or so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The movie opens on Crystal Lake&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. A couple of high school kids are fooling around on a boat. An unfortunate sequence of events sees Jason resurrected from his watery grave via electricity. He makes short work of the two teens, reclaiming his trademark hockey mask in the process&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to the following morning. The &lt;em&gt;SS Lazarus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is about to set sail for New York City, with the local graduating high school class on board. One of the kids, Rennie, is late to arrive. She was reluctant to come, due to a deep fear of the water after almost drowning as a child. Her English teacher, Miss Van Deusen, convinced her. Van Deusen is chaperoning the trip along with Mr. McCulloch, a pompous biology teacher who’s also Rennie’s uncle and legal guardian. McCulloch isn’t happy, but Rennie is determined to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they set off, Jason sneaks on board and begins picking off the teens. While he goes about his work we’re presented with a series of sub-plots. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rennie has visions of a small boy drowning. Haughty prom queen Tamara tries to blackmail McCulloch by seducing him on video. The captain’s son, Sean, fails to live up to his father’s expectation that he do the nautical equivalent of backing the car out of the garage. Another teen, Julius, shows he’s a hell of a boxer&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn4&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a while, Jason kills the captain. Sean discovers his father’s body and alerts the rest of the passengers. The kids arm themselves and attempt to hunt down Jason. But a series of events causes the ship to sink. Sean, Rennie, Julius, McCulloch and Van Deusen manage to get into a life boat and row to the shores of New York City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Jason’s right behind them, determined to finish what he started aboard the boat. The finale sees Rennie and Sean running from Jason through a sewer tunnel that’s due to be flushed with toxic waste. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This installment was the lowest grossing entry in the series. But that’s less a reflection on this film and more a confirmation that the previous installment, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews/friday-the-13th-part-vii-the-new-blood-1988/&quot;&gt;Friday the 13th Part VII: The New Blood (1988)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, killed the franchise. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; film was awful. This movie is bad, but nowhere near &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; level of terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, much like the previous film, this entry saddles the protagonist with a useless melodramatic sub plot. But the supporting cast here is far more tolerable. And the film doesn’t take itself too seriously. There are a couple of good laughs&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn5&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, the majority of the film does take place on a boat. But if it didn’t have the Manhattan title, I doubt fans would have minded so much. At this point in the series, &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; change of scenery would be welcome. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the most disappointing aspect of this entry is not how long it takes to get to New York. It’s that once it gets there, Jason gets tunnel vision. He doesn’t care about anyone but the people from the boat. He walks through swaths of pedestrians and ignores them. Jason in a major city should be a one-man apocalypse, killing anyone and anything within reach. He does off some street punks, but that&amp;#39;s about it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end, &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th Part VIII: Jason Takes Manhattan&lt;/em&gt; is more disappointing than awful. Aside from a change of scenery, it doesn’t offer anything we haven’t seen done better before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is Crystal Lake an inlet now? The film doesn’t make it clear.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is ridiculous. One of the kids gets a hockey mask to scare the other, but it happens to be the exact same kind Jason wore. Right down to the chunk missing due to the axe-to-the-face Jason suffered at the end of &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th Part III (1982)&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good name.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn4&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because, why wouldn’t a school-sponsored trip to New York City include a little boxing on the way?&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref4&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn5&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two scenes made me chuckle. The first was the culmination of the fight between Jason and Julius. The second was when Jason flips up his mask to the street gang after knocking over their boom-box. Good bits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref5&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>19. Friday the 13th Part VII: The New Blood (1988) ★☆☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/friday-the-13th-part-vii-the-new-blood-1988/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/friday-the-13th-part-vii-the-new-blood-1988</id><updated>2015-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a lesson here. I came to &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th Part VII: The New Blood&lt;/em&gt; with an open mind. Sure, I&amp;#39;d heard rumblings that it was bad, but I didn&amp;#39;t read any reviews in advance. I didn&amp;#39;t want to let the masses make up my mind. I&amp;#39;ve seen enough supposedly awful films to know the masses can be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story opens outside a house on Crystal Lake. We see a young girl standing outside the door. Inside, we hear her parents fighting. The mom&amp;#39;s yelling that the dad promised he wouldn&amp;#39;t drink so much. The dad&amp;#39;s telling her to shut up and smacking her around. It aims for drama but plays like caricature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The girl runs down to the lake, walks the length of a short pier, and gets in a small fishing boat. She motors out to the middle of the lake. The dad comes running out of the house down to the pier&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. He yells for her to come back. The mom comes out of the house and joins in the yelling. The dad advances down the pier. The little girl gives the dad the stink-eye of death and the pier starts to shake. Not a rumble, but a full-on cartoonish wobble with the pylons jutting several feet into the air. It&amp;#39;s an expensive-looking mechanical effect, but laughable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pier crumbles down, taking the dad with it. We flash forward to the little girl, now seventeen&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Her name is Tina. She hasn’t been back to Crystal Lake since that day. She&amp;#39;s returning now, along with her mother, at the coaxing of her smarmy psychiatrist, Dr. Crews. The good doctor says she must confront the death of her father by revisiting the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tina and her mother arrive at the lake house. Dr. Crews is there waiting. There&amp;#39;s also a house full of teens next door. One of them takes an instant interest in Tina. Perhaps he sees something we don&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few needless scenes later, Tina inadvertently wakes up Jason via her telekinesis&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Jason sets to work massacring the teens next door&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn4&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Tina’s mom uncovers Dr. Crews’ true intentions. There&amp;#39;s a lot of over emoting and dues ex machina that culminates in a showdown between Tina and Jason. Tina uses her telekinetic powers to hurl flower pots at Jason. There&amp;#39;s a big explosion and a head-scratching ending, then it&amp;#39;s all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so the masses were right. This is an awful movie. Sitting through it was a chore. Like the song says, sometimes bad is bad. Lesson learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;#39;s look on the bright side. Zombie Jason looks great. He&amp;#39;s a big hulking monster. This entry also sees Jason make use of power tools&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn5&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s it for the bright side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This installment attempts to replicate the scenario from &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews/friday-the-13th-the-final-chapter-1984/&quot;&gt;Friday the 13th: The Final Chapter (1984)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. A house full of teens next to a house with a single mom and her teenage daughter. Had it just done that, things might not have been so bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it had to tack on a sub-plot involving telekinetic Tina, her mother, and Dr. Crews. This is the worst part of the film. More than once, I ached to fast-forward through these scenes. They aren&amp;#39;t just bad. They&amp;#39;re like a crying baby on an airplane. You just want it to stop. I don’t fault the performers, they&amp;#39;re only working with what they&amp;#39;re given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, Tina is the worst. Her character is an ineffectual protagonist who spends most of the film in histrionics. The worst kind of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_girl&quot;&gt;final girl&lt;/a&gt;. The film expects us to care about her without giving us a reason for doing so. When the other kids take an instant dislike to her, we’re on their side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And speaking of those kids, they have no chemistry between them. They feel like strangers thrown together rather than friends. None of them register. Their scenes are dull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this wouldn’t be so bad if the film didn&amp;#39;t take itself so seriously. The black humor in the previous entry is gone. So is the manic campiness that accompanied &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews/friday-the-13th-a-new-beginning-1985/&quot;&gt;Friday the 13th: A New Beginning (1985)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Instead we&amp;#39;re asked to suffer through scenes alternating between idle boredom and overwrought melodrama. When Jason offs one of the characters it is a relief. Not because it breaks some nonexistent tension, but because we’re one step closer to the film’s end. In &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th Part VII: The New Blood&lt;/em&gt;, it’s the audience, not Jason’s quarry, that suffers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first thought upon seeing the Dad: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuart_Smalley&quot;&gt;Stewart Smalley&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting this entry in the then-future of 2001. I wonder how many fans realized this back in 1988.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason wound up chained to the bottom of Crystal Lake at the end of the previous film. Exactly how Tina’s telekinesis revives him is never explained. As for the telekinesis itself, in his &lt;a href=&quot;http://horror-movie-a-day.blogspot.com/2009/01/friday-13th-part-vii-new-blood.html&quot;&gt;review on Horror Movie A Day&lt;/a&gt;, Brian Collins speculates that it was a response to the higher grossing &lt;em&gt;A Nightmare on Elm Street&lt;/em&gt; franchise. &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn4&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The movie should be over right here. Tina resurrects Jason, passing out in the process. Jason marches out of the water and dismembers the unconscious Tina. But no. Jason marches past her and the two houses and goes a couple of miles up the road to off a pair of teens before circling back to continue his rampage. &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref4&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn5&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though, with supernatural strength, one wonders why he bothers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref5&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>18. Jason Lives: Friday the 13th Part VI (1986) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/jason-lives-friday-the-13th-part-vi-1986/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/jason-lives-friday-the-13th-part-vi-1986</id><updated>2015-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Jason lives. Not &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th Part VI: Jason Lives&lt;/em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;Jason Lives: Friday the 13th Part VI&lt;/em&gt;. After the head-scratching mess that was &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews/friday-the-13th-a-new-beginning-1985/&quot;&gt;Friday the 13th: A New Beginning (1985)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, somebody in Paramount’s marketing division must have worried that kids would stop reading after the &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th&lt;/em&gt; part of the title. I’m not sure things were that dire, but it does give you a sense of this film’s mandate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry more or less ignores the last film’s events. It opens with Tommy Jarvis determined to rid himself of the specter of Jason. To that end, he plans to dig up Jason’s corpse and incinerate it. He&amp;#39;s even brought a buddy along for help&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tommy and his friend dig up the corpse all right, but a bolt of lightening reanimates the maggot-filled carcass. Undead Jason makes short work of Tommy&amp;#39;s pal, but Tommy manages to escape and attempts to warn the local sheriff. The sheriff, of course, doesn&amp;#39;t believe Tommy and runs him out of town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Jason resumes his murderous ways. He offs some corporate paintballers, and a few teen camp counselors before Tommy gets back to town. Thinking Tommy committed the murders himself, the sheriff locks Tommy up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to worry though, the sheriff’s plucky teen daughter frees Tommy from his cell. Using a plan Tommy gleaned from reading a book on the occult, the two head to Camp Crystal Lake to stop Jason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry cements Jason’s transition from deranged madman to supernatural monster. Jason now has super human strength. Bullets can&amp;#39;t kill him. Early on, Tommy looks to incinerate Jason, but the skies open up and the resulting rain prevents Tommy from striking a match. It’s a nice nod that casts Jason as something of a force of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This installment also sports a nice streak of self-referential black comedy. Consider the scene where Jason stalks a group of children. One of the boys looks at another and asks sarcastically: “So, what &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; you want to be when you grew up?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, when ever Jason&amp;#39;s on screen this entry&amp;#39;s a lot of fun. Unfortunately, the plot revolves around Tommy. A better script would have killed him off in the film&amp;#39;s opening sequence. Instead, we suffer through a tired &amp;quot;boy who cried wolf&amp;quot; plot that never pays off, and cringe at the stilted melodrama with the sheriff’s daughter.  A stronger performer might have been able to rise above the material. But Thom Mathews’ performance as Tommy kept reminding me of Michael Dudikoff in &lt;em&gt;American Ninja (1985)&lt;/em&gt;. Minus the ninja bad-assery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus on Tommy comes at the expense of the supporting cast. Almost all of  Jason&amp;#39;s victim fail to register. The female camp counselors in particular felt interchangeable. They exist only as fodder for Jason and thus, when Jason’s not on screen, they’re boring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jason Lives: Friday the 13th Part VI&lt;/em&gt; isn’t an awful movie. The depiction of Jason is great, and the fourth-wall humor is a nice touch. But the forced melodrama and bland supporting cast drag things down. The only character we’re interested in is Jason and when he’s off screen, this entry is a snooze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ron Palillo, TV’s Horshak!&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>17. Friday the 13th: A New Beginning (1985) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/friday-the-13th-a-new-beginning-1985/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/friday-the-13th-a-new-beginning-1985</id><updated>2014-12-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What were they thinking?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That about sums up my reaction to &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th: A New Beginning&lt;/em&gt;. After nailing the formula in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews/friday-the-13th-the-final-chapter-1984/&quot;&gt;Friday the 13th: The Final Chapter (1984)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, they throw everything out the window and nearly kill the franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry follows Tommy, the young boy who survived the previous film by hacking Jason’s body to pieces with a machete. He&amp;#39;s seventeen now, and in a startling bit of plausibility, has spent the previous six years in a mental institution&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tommy is a lackluster protagonist. He&amp;#39;s superficial to the plot and says less than two-dozen words throughout the film. He spends most of his time either looking confused or violently acting out&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film opens with Tommy arriving at a kind of halfway house for annoying teens&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. After one of the kids offs another with an axe, an unseen assailant begins murdering teens, staff, and pretty much everyone on screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harkening back to the original  &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th (1980)&lt;/em&gt;, this entry is less a monster movie and more of a mystery thriller. But the execution is sloppy. Characters are introduced and killed in the same scene. Several of the performances, such as the backwoods mother and son living adjacent to the halfway house, veer well into camp. Worst of all, the eventual reveal is unsatisfying. It relies on some awkward exposition to explain the killer’s motive and even then makes little sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But time has been kind to &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th: A New Beginning&lt;/em&gt;. Knowing that the franchise rights itself, fans can appreciate this entry in a so-bad-it’s-good kind of way. The nonsense plot, Tommy’s non-dialog, and the over-the-top performances are all good for a laugh. One of the characters even dies in an outhouse after eating some spicy enchiladas. What were they thinking, indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This puts the film in the then-future of 1990&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I had to look this up. The series timeline gets really crazy from here on out as they keep skipping forward in time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This petulant behavior may be a remnant of an earlier draft of the script. According to the IMDb, Cory Feldman was going to reprise his role as Tommy. But when he was unavailable due to The Goonies (1985), the filmmakers rewrote the part for an older actor. One suspects it was a very quick rewrite.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not made clear, but one presumes the state is transferring Tommy since he&amp;#39;ll soon age out of the system. But what happened to his sister?&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>16. Horror of Dracula (1958) ★★★★★</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/horror-of-dracula-1958/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/horror-of-dracula-1958</id><updated>2014-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Howard Hawks once said that a good movie consisted of  &amp;quot;three great scenes and no bad ones.&amp;quot; Hammer&amp;#39;s first entry in its &lt;em&gt;Dracula&lt;/em&gt; franchise gives us exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first great scene comes early. Jonathan Harker has arrived at Castle Dracula posing as a librarian.  While prowling the castle&amp;#39;s corridors at night, he finds a young woman. She sports ruby red lips, brilliant blue eyes and ample cleavage. She is terrified. She claims she’s being held prisoner. She begs Harker to help her escape. Harker feigns ignorance. She persists. His resolve weakens. He agrees to help her. Grateful, she bursts into tears and buries her head in his shoulder. The music shifts. We see her blue eyes fix on Harker’s neck. Her head tilts back as her eyes close. Her ruby red lips draw back to reveal fangs. She bites Harker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as she does, Dracula (Christopher Lee) bursts into the room with a piercing shriek. Lee is feral and demonic. Shown in close up, His eyes are bloodshot red. His gore-smeared sneer reveals blood-covered fangs. The shot lasts all of a few seconds, but it still packs a punch. This is Dracula in all his visceral glory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second great scene happens at about the three-quarters mark. Dracula has turned Harker&amp;#39;s fiancee Lucy who&amp;#39;s now preying on children. Lucy&amp;#39;s brother Arthur has gone to her crypt at night, to assure himself that she’s not a vampire. To Arthur’s horror, he finds Lucy returning to her tomb, leading a young girl. Lucy&amp;#39;s eyes light up with more than just brotherly love. “Come, let me kiss you,” she says to Arthur. She advances, baring her fangs, but Arthur stands transfixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before she can consummate the act, Van Helsing (Peter Cushing) appears and thrusts a crucifix into her face. She backs away in agony. Van Helsing, jaw set, eyes full of cold detachment, advances. She&amp;#39;s cornered. Van Helsing presses the crucifix to her forehead. The flesh smolders and burns, leaving the imprint of the cross. Van Helsing stares down, unmoved. Lucy shrieks and flees into her tomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a crackerjack scene that works just as well today as it did half a century ago. The practical effects still look great and Cushing&amp;#39;s performance in the scene is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third great scene is the finale. Arthur and Van Helsing have chased Dracula back to his castle. Dawn is fast approaching. Van Helsing catches the count before he can disappear down a secret passage. The two grapple. The count looks to have the upper hand until Van Helsing vaults atop a long table, runs the length and launches himself into the air, grabbing the wall&amp;#39;s tapestry curtains as he lands, pulling them down to let in the morning sun. Dracula tries to flee, but Van Helsing pins him in place by fashioning a make-shift crucifix out of candle holders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The swashbuckling acrobatics cement Van Helsing  as the heroic foil to the villainous Count. Cushing&amp;#39;s Van Helsing isn&amp;#39;t just a wise man with a strong will, he&amp;#39;s a man of action. The iconic monster hunter out to rid the world of supernatural evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vacillate between this film and &lt;em&gt;Dracula (1931)&lt;/em&gt; for my favorite interpretation of the Count. I prefer Lee’s grittier performance, but I dislike the overt physicality. His Dracula runs, grapples, and digs holes&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It makes for more action on screen, but it also lends the character a vulnerability that softens his edge. Also, Lee doesn&amp;#39;t have any dialog apart from his introductory scene, which is a shame. A battle of wills scene between Cushing and Lee would have been dynamite&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Consider how the classic line, &amp;quot;You are very wise for one who has lived but a single lifetime,” would sound in Lee’s ominous baritone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, &lt;em&gt;Dracula&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Horror of Dracula&lt;/em&gt; here in the US) is a great film. Buoyed by two iconic leads in Cushing and Lee, it rolls along at a terrific pace.  By paring down the supporting cast and playing up the sex and gore, it makes the familiar plot feel fresh and new. It turns a gothic horror story into a thrilling adventure. Hawks&amp;#39; definition of a great movie may be a bit simplistic, but &lt;em&gt;Dracula&lt;/em&gt; is proof that simple can work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hole-digging scene always throws me. Why wouldn’t he put her in the crypt? And how does he happen to have a shovel handy?&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a shame that Lee and Cushing wouldn’t meet again as Dracula and Van Helsing until the disappointing &lt;em&gt;Dracula A.D. 1972 (1972)&lt;/em&gt;. Cushing starred in the immediate sequel &lt;em&gt;The Brides of Dracula (1960)&lt;/em&gt; which lacked Lee. Lee returned in the third installment &lt;em&gt;Dracula: Prince of Darkness (1966)&lt;/em&gt; which lacked Cushing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>15. Interstellar (2014) ★★★☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/interstellar-2014/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/interstellar-2014</id><updated>2014-12-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;I know where &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; went wrong. I knew the instant it happened. I may have let out a small groan. But I’m getting ahead of myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s three or four generations into the future. The earth is drying up. Giant dust storms ravage the land. Blight has wiped out all the world’s crops except corn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matthew McConaughey plays Cooper, a former test pilot/engineer who, like just about everyone else, has been forced into farming to survive. He hates it, but he does it to support his two young children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A series of gravitational anomalies lead him to the remnants of NASA. NASA has a plan to save humanity. They’ve discovered a wormhole near Saturn. On the other side are potentially hospitable worlds. They’ve got a ship and crew ready. They just need a pilot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooper agrees, even though the length of the journey means he’ll miss years of his children’s lives. If he makes it back at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flight goes smoothly and the crew passes through the wormhole in a sequence that begs favorable comparisons with &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey (1968)&lt;/em&gt;. On the other side they assess their situation. There are three potential worlds, but the closest and most promising orbits the outskirts of a black hole. This creates a warping effect with time. An hour spent on the surface of the planet equates to seven years back on earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They agree to be quick. Cooper pilots a shuttle craft with two other scientists down to the planet&amp;#39;s surface. The plan is to be in-and-out, but of course, there are complications. They return to the main craft just over three hours later, only to find that twenty three years have passed on earth. Cooper checks the equivalent of his mail in the form of video messages. He sees his son graduate high school, meet a girl, and get married. He sees the birth and death of his grandson. Finally, he sees his son, now a man older than himself, say goodbye, resigned that Cooper is never coming back. Cooper has missed it all. It flattens him and us. Never has a movie conveyed the isolation of space travel like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, Cooper gets a message from his daughter. They had a rough falling out as he left. She felt he was abandoning her. Now, she’s a full grown woman, the same age as him. But she’s still bitter at him for leaving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this brings us to the point I mentioned earlier. The point where Interstellar loses its way. The film cuts to Cooper’s daughter as she finishes her message. Now we’re back on earth. No longer alone. Now, we have parallel stories, Cooper in space and Cooper’s family on earth. What started as a meditation on mankind transcending earth devolves into a predictable melodrama. The effects are fantastic, and there are some nail-biting set pieces, but the film has nothing new to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s tempting to think that &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt;’s reach exceeded its grasp. That it tried and failed. I don’t think it tried at all. Rather than explore new themes it settled for the comfort of familiar dramatic scenarios. Granted, it executes those tropes with masterful precision. But &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt; had the chance to transcend the science fiction genre. Instead, it abandoned it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>14. Friday the 13th: The Final Chapter (1984) ★★★☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/friday-the-13th-the-final-chapter-1984/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/friday-the-13th-the-final-chapter-1984</id><updated>2014-12-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Now, I know what some of you are thinking: &lt;em&gt;How can he give a piece of trash like this three stars?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hear me out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this movie came out, I was still waking up Saturday mornings to watch cartoons. All I knew of &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th&lt;/em&gt; came from looking at the box covers in the video store. I was sure those white body outlines holding bloody knives and axes were gateways to pure, brutal terror. So, of course, I wanted to watch them. But I never did. Neither did any of my friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s an odd sense of nostalgia that draws me to the films now. Of course, they’re not as scary as my young self believed. But watching them takes part of me back to the days of looking for prizes in breakfast cereals. Back when a monster as simple as Jason represented the pinnacle of terror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry is likely the best of the series. It picks up right where &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th Part III (1982)&lt;/em&gt; leaves off&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Hanged after suffering a hatchet to the face, Jason is dead. The police cart him off to the morgue where he&amp;#39;s bagged and tagged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, he’s not dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jason wakes up and dispatches some of the improbably young hospital staff. Then he heads back to Crystal Lake where he works his way through a house full of oversexed teens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This film operates based on a simple formula: Titillate the audience via some nudity, then have Jason dispatch someone in a gruesomely over-the-top fashion&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  To that end, it delivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what elevates this entry above the rest of the series is how it handles the cast of teen victims. For most of the film, they are unaware of Jason, or any suspicious goings on. They&amp;#39;re in their own movie, complete with their own sub-plots. Granted, those sub-plots amount to little more than a bad teen sex comedy, but they hold our interest when Jason&amp;#39;s off-screen&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Jason doesn&amp;#39;t so much stalk these teens as pick them off at will. He&amp;#39;s no longer just a deranged man with a knife. He&amp;#39;s a true monster&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn4&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. A demon with a machete. He marches  through the film as an unstoppable, inhuman force of evil. He doesn&amp;#39;t run. Running implies chasing which suggest the possibility of escape. In this film, Jason is not an assailant, he is an inevitability&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn5&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is an amalgam of gratuitous nudity and creative violence. It&amp;#39;s pure exploitation, sure, but it never pretends to be anything more. I can respect that. And I can enjoy the visceral thrills that a good exploitation picture delivers.  &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th: The Final Chapter&lt;/em&gt; isn&amp;#39;t a great movie, but it&amp;#39;s everything my younger self could have hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Films two, three and four happen back-to-back, taking place over the course of four days. This entry starts the night of Sunday the 15th, and ends on Tuesday the 17th. This proves to be something of a problem, however. See, one of the characters is out to avenge his dead sister, who Jason killed in the second film. This character has all kinds of newspaper clippings about Jason that he’s been compiling since his sister died. Except, by the film’s timeline, his sister died less than 48 hours ago.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th&lt;/em&gt; films are far from the only horror movies to do this. One of &lt;em&gt;Alien (1979)&lt;/em&gt;’s best scares comes after the camera lingers on a wall full of posters of nude women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also helps that Crispin Glover&amp;#39;s performance foreshadows his turn in &lt;em&gt;Back to the Future (1985)&lt;/em&gt;. His dancing scene alone almost makes the film worth a look.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn4&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews/jason-lives-friday-the-13th-part-vi-1986/&quot;&gt;Jason Lives: Friday the 13th Part VI (1986)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; cements this personification by turning him into a kind of Frankenstein&amp;#39;s monster.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref4&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn5&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider this an explanation of how Jason seems to teleport around the house. He goes from outside the second floor window to inside the first floor kitchen in a matter of seconds without making a sound.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref5&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>13. How I Grade</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/features/how-i-grade/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/features/how-i-grade</id><updated>2014-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;a great movie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;5 stars&quot; src=&quot;images/5-stars-4661cb2a.svg&quot; /&gt; I loved it. A must-see. A perfect or nearly perfect movie. These are the movies I recommend to everyone. This is a hard rating to earn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;a good movie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;4 stars&quot; src=&quot;images/4-stars-92a55331.svg&quot; /&gt; I really liked it. Unless you hate the genre or the star, you should watch it. These are the movies I recommend to most folks. They may not resonate like the 5-star selections, but they don&amp;#39;t disappoint either. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;an okay movie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;3 stars&quot; src=&quot;images/3-stars-ebc473a3.svg&quot; /&gt; I liked it. I wouldn&amp;#39;t recommend it, but I wouldn&amp;#39;t necessarily recommend &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; it either. A good rule of thumb: If I liked it but can&amp;#39;t remember a line of dialog one-week later, it was just okay. Many a summer blockbuster falls into this category. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;a bad movie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;2 stars&quot; src=&quot;images/2-stars-9f281273.svg&quot; /&gt; I didn&amp;#39;t like it. Unless you have a deep-seeded love for the genre or star, avoid this. Maybe it had a moment or two of goodness, but it was a disappointment. If I paid money to see it, I felt burned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;an awful movie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;1 star&quot; src=&quot;images/1-star-a314fc32.svg&quot; /&gt; I hated it. Not even in the “so-bad-it&amp;#39;s-good” sense. Everyone involved should apologize. This too is a hard rating to earn. When reading a 1-star review, remember: I watch them so you don&amp;#39;t have to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;On Grading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s start with a binary scale. A yes or no. Gene Siskel based the famous &amp;#39;Thumbs up/Thumbs down&amp;#39; system on the thought that a person just wants to know: “Should I see this movie?” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a pragmatic approach, but how do you separate the good from the great? Put another way, both &lt;em&gt;Batman Begins&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Dark Knight&lt;/em&gt; would get a &amp;quot;Thumbs up&amp;quot; but they are not equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the star scale. I&amp;#39;ve seen scales with three stars all the way up to ten, sometimes with half-stars between. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all star-systems are equal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roger Ebert hated the four-star scale his paper used because it offered no middle ground.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; He&amp;#39;s right, with no middle ground every movie must be either good or bad. Most movies are just okay. Thus, we can rule out the four-star system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, let&amp;#39;s consider the iMDb. It uses a ten-star system. That’s a lot of stars. In 2009 the median movie score was a 6.6. This implies that users are skewing toward the upper bounds. Defining the ratings could mitigate this, but that in itself is a challenge. If a 1-star rating means you hated it, and a 10-star rating means you loved it, what does a 3-star rating mean? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if four is too small and ten is too large, what&amp;#39;s ideal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the 5-star system. Ebert liked it too&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It offers a middle ground (3-stars) while remaining small enough to allow for discreet rating definitions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what about letter grade systems?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I quite like them. They&amp;#39;re essentially a five-star system with an ‘A’ as 5-stars, a ‘B’ as 4-stars and so on. I use a letter grade system behind the scenes because it&amp;#39;s how my brain works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why display them as stars? Well, for one, grade definitions aren&amp;#39;t universal. To me, a ’C’ grade means an “okay” movie, to others it means a bad movie. A 3-star out of 5 display makes it clear it&amp;#39;s a middle-of-the-road rating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other reason is Netflix. With the service&amp;#39;s rise in popularity, I decided to synchronize my grades with their review system. Thus, if you&amp;#39;ve rated movies on Netflix, my definitions will be familiar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grading systems are harder than one would think. It&amp;#39;s all about nuance. I think a 5-star system works, but I’m not married to the idea. Some of my favorite reviewers don’t rate at all. They’d rather you just read the review. Fair enough, but I bet they rate titles on Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ebert, Roger, “You Give Out Too Many Stars”, &lt;em&gt;Roger Ebert&lt;/em&gt; , last modified September 14, 2008, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rogerebert.com/rogers-journal/you-give-out-too-many-stars&quot;&gt;http://www.rogerebert.com/rogers-journal/you-give-out-too-many-stars&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ebert also argues that &lt;em&gt;readers&lt;/em&gt; dislike scales with a middle ground, but I disagree. We all know what it means for a movie to be just “okay.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.avclub.com/film/&quot;&gt;The Onion A.V. Club&lt;/a&gt; makes great use of letter grades.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>12. The Hunger Games: Mockingjay - Part 1 (2014) ★☆☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-hunger-games-mockingjay-part-1-2014/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-hunger-games-mockingjay-part-1-2014</id><updated>2014-12-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Full disclosure: I haven&amp;#39;t seen the first two &lt;em&gt;Hunger Games&lt;/em&gt; films, nor have I read the books. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the film did an admirable job of bringing me up to speed. Our heroine, Katniss Everdeen (Jennifer Lawrence) has just destroyed the titular Hunger Games, dealing a symbolic blow to the evil Capitol. Rebel forces have rescued her, but they were unable to rescue her true love Peeta, who&amp;#39;s now in the Capitol&amp;#39;s clutches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the part where I try and tell you what the movie was about. But I am at a loss. Watching this film felt like watching the deleted scenes from a better movie. A movie where things actually happen. &lt;em&gt;The Hunger Games: Mockingjay - Part 1&lt;/em&gt; has little to no plot, and the characters end the film more or less where they started. Katniss frets about Peeta, walks through a lot of rubble-strewn towns, and frets about Peeta some more. You could condense the entire film into fifteen minutes and not lose a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;The Hunger Games: Mockingjay - Part 1&lt;/em&gt; is not fifteen minutes. It&amp;#39;s just over two hours long. Two hours of nothing but filler. It’s inexcusable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m not saying a movie needs action. A meditation on Katniss being caught as pawn between the two forces vying for control of a dystopian society could be interesting if the sides weren&amp;#39;t so black and white. The capital is evil and the rebels are good. With no gray area, the film loses any shot at a creditable political commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Lawrence is a good actress capable of commanding your attention on screen, but you wouldn&amp;#39;t know it from watching this movie. Between the ill-fitting jump suit and pale makeup, she looks every bit as listless as the script. Her supporting cast includes Philip Seymour Hoffman and Julianne Moore. To their credit, they do a good job of not rolling their eyes at the dialog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hunger Games: Mockingjay - Part 1&lt;/em&gt; is a non-movie. It has no reason to exist outside of gouging fans of the series for the cost of an extra ticket. Just skip straight to the real finale in  &lt;em&gt;The Hunger Games: Mockingjay - Part 2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>