<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?><feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'><title>Frank's Movie Log</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/feed.xml' rel='self' /><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com' /><updated>2015-03-02T20:28:32-05:00</updated><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com</id><author><name>Frank Showalter</name></author><entry><title>34. To the Devil a Daughter (1976) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/to-the-devil-a-daughter-1976/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/to-the-devil-a-daughter-1976</id><updated>2015-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To the Devil a Daughter&lt;/em&gt; was the final film of Hammer Film Productions&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The studio rose to prominence with films such as &lt;em&gt;Curse of Frankenstein (1957)&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews/horror-of-dracula-1958/&quot;&gt;Horror of Dracula (1958)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Unlike those staged, period pieces, this film is set in contemporary times and shot on location. It represented a big departure for Hammer, but it was too little too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story—ah, well, you’ll have to bear with me here. I’ve seen the movie twice and I’m still not sure about some of the details. According the featurette on Anchor Bay’s DVD, the filmmaker’s were writing the script as they went along. It shows in the final product. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As near as I can tell, Father Michael, played by Christopher Lee, is a priest who commits the heresy of putting his faith in man over God. To that end—and here’s where things get fuzzy—he retreats to a compound in Bavaria where he forms his own Satanic religion which masquerades as Catholicism. One of his acolytes dies during childbirth and Father Michael baptizes the baby, a girl, in her dead mother’s blood. The girl, Catherine, grows up as a nun in Father Michael’s compound. On her eighteenth birthday she travels to London. There, Father Michael will baptize her in the blood of a demon creature birthed by another of Father Michael’s acolytes&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, fortunately for humanity, Catherine’s father, Henry, has a change of heart. Henry appeals to occult novelist John Verney, played by Richard Widmark. Verney intercepts Catherine at Heathrow airport. Verney had hoped to get a book out of Henry’s story, but soon realizes the stakes are much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Father Michael attempts to reclaim Catherine by possessing her. Verney tries to keep her safe. During the tug-of-war we’re presented with a couple of disturbing scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first concerns the birth of the demon creature. Picture a staged, antiseptic facsimile of a young girl&amp;#39;s bedroom. On the bed, a woman prepares to give birth. Strips of white cloth bind her wrists to the headboard and clamp her knees and ankles shut, giving the baby no escape. Arms spread, knees clenched, she lays crucified. Her face glistens with sweat as her back arches and her body spasms from another contraction. Her belly swells. Beside her, Father Michael stands waiting, smiling with eager eyes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And later, we see one of Catherine’s visions/dreams. We’re looking through her eyes. She’s pregnant and laying on her back. We see her bulging womb. Her legs are open, knees up, in the traditional birthing position. Still through her eyes, we see something crawling up from between her legs. At first glimpse it seems to be a baby, but no, it&amp;#39;s a horrid combination of baby and beast with a monstrous jaw and reptilian eyes. Covered in blood, it writhes between her legs, smearing her thighs and stomach with gore. She reaches down and strokes the creature&amp;#39;s grotesque head. Now her midsection is awash in thick, almost syrupy, blood as she gently pushes the thing back down, between her legs. Still through her eyes, we hear her moan in a mixture of agony and ecstasy as she forces the monstrosity &lt;em&gt;back up into her womb&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality of the creature effects in this scene is laughable. And what’s worse the scene has little to do with the story. Instead, it feels like something tacked on as a reaction to &lt;em&gt;Rosemary’s Baby (1968)&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Exorcist (1973)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s when you compare this film to those, that one realizes how far Hammer had fallen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a studio that, nineteen years prior, had revived the horror genre by injecting a liberal dose of gore and sex into the monster movie. The resulting films were edgy and fresh. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But time passed. By the time this film came out, Hammer’s core audience now had kids of their own. Hammer’s period monster movies were passé. They were your &lt;em&gt;parent’s&lt;/em&gt; horror movies. Even this wave of satanic themed films was on it’s nadir. Two years later &lt;em&gt;Halloween (1978)&lt;/em&gt; would usher in the slasher genre that would dominate horror for the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time Hammer woke up and tried to tap into the mainstream horror pulse, it lacked the resources to pull off a competent film. Christopher Lee does his best, but Richard Widmark looks tired and annoyed. He’s just cashing a paycheck. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst part is the ending. Remember how I said they were writing the script as they went along? As it turns out, they ran out of money by the time they got to the end. After an hour and a half of buildup, Verney and Father Michael square off in a mausoleum. Father Michael stands in a large circle made of blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Says Verney, “You really think this circle will protect you, don’t you? It won’t.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But it will,” says Father Michael. “Because this circle stands upon a hill of flint, and flint is the sacred stone of Astaroth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verney holds up a rock he literally just picked up five minutes earlier and used to club one of Father Michael’s henchman. “But this sacred stone of Astaroth has the blood of your disciple on it. Now, the demons will protect me.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verney steps into the circle and throws the rock at Father Michael, hitting him on the head. Father Michael falls to the ground and disappears. Movie over. That’s the ending. A mumbo-jumbo bit of rock-paper-scissors involving flint and the blood of a disciple. Two bits of information &lt;em&gt;never mentioned in the film before&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this was the best Hammer could do, then the studio’s death was a mercy killing&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until the studio was resurrected in 2008.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m willing to give the film the benefit of the doubt and assume Father Michael wasn’t doing this for Satan, but for his own gain. That he’s somehow brought about the birth of a demon and by baptizing Catherine in its blood, he could control its power. I know that’s reaching, but I’ve got a soft spot for Hammer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so the studio didn’t &lt;em&gt;die&lt;/em&gt;, it just produced television instead of movies. &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>33. The Long Night (1947) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-long-night-1947/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-long-night-1947</id><updated>2015-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Long Night&lt;/em&gt; is one of those films that starts well only to lose its way in the third act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story starts with a murder. We’re inside an apartment building on the working-class side of the tracks. We hear gunshots. A man staggers out of a unit holding his gut and tumbles down the stairs. The police arrive. They attempt to extract the shooter. Through a door, the shooter says he wants to be left alone. We recognize the voice as Henry Fonda’s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through flashbacks, we learn that Henry Fonda plays Joe, a veteran recently returned from World War II. He’s a wholesome guy. He drinks milk and uses exclamations like, “No kidding!” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, while working as a sandblaster at the local plant, Joe meets a young girl named Jo Anne, played by Barbara Bel Geddes. Joe and Jo Anne hit it off. The film would have us believe this is natural since they’re both orphans and they’re both named Joe. They begin dating. Joe falls hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One night, Jo Anne cancels a date with Joe. She has something to do. Joe says that’s fine, but takes Jo Anne’s favorite stuffed animal hostage as a bit of insurance that she’ll see him again. It’s a nice touch that gives Joe some edge and helps make the film’s later events more plausible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe ends up tailing Jo Anne to a dingy club where a magician is performing. Vincent Price plays the magician. We recognize him as the man who was shot during the film’s opening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the bar, Joe meets Charlene, played by Ann Dvorak. Through Charlene, we learn the magician’s name is Maximilian. Charlene was one of his assistants. She’s just now decided to leave him, having grown tired of his manipulative ways. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe watches Jo Anne watching Maximilian. She seems enraptured by his performance. After the show, she approaches him and he tells her to meet him at his table. Joe’s seen enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before joining Jo Anne, however, Maximilian approaches Joe and Charlene at the bar. It’s here we get our first taste of Maximilian’s condescending wit. He tries to cajole Charlene into changing her mind. Joe tells Maximilian to scram. Maximilian replies with a sarcastic grin, “My friend, there is no one I would like disagreeing with more than you. However, under the circumstances, there’s hardly any point in continuing our conversation.” Then, to Charlene, “Till tomorrow, my dear.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charlene develops a torch for Joe. Joe, feeling hurt by Jo Anne, uses Charlene for companionship. She’s more or less emotional collateral damage by the film’s end. Dvorak makes the most of a part that exists only to show Joe turning to the dark side when he thinks he’s lost Jo Anne. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the story goes on, we learn the depths of Maximilian’s debauchery. How he’s seduced and manipulated countless naive young girls like Jo Anne. Each new bit of knowledge cuts at Joe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all builds to a showdown between Joe and Maximilian. The confrontation doesn’t disappoint. Price is great in the part despite being a decade too young. Like all of Price’s best roles, he plays a showman, one capable of immense charm on stage, and immense debauchery off stage. He talks circles around Fonda, each word dripping with condescension. Fonda plays on this, his frustration building and building until it boils over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to where we came in. And here’s where movie goes wrong. The tone shifts from noir to populist drama. The town rallies around Joe in his standoff with the police. Jo Anne fights through a never-ending mob in an effort to reach Joe. She’s knocked down by someone carrying a bicycle. Won’t the police please just let her talk to Joe, she pleads. But they won’t. Which leads to more shots of Jo Anne fighting her way through the crowd. As if this all weren’t bad enough, the film closes on a cornball line. As he’s escorted out by the police, Joe asks one of the crowd for a light. The man lights Joe’s cigarette and asks, “How you doing, Joe?” Joe replies, “I think we’ll make it, Freddy. Just about make it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No Joe, not with a disingenuous ending like that, you won’t.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>32. Kingsman: The Secret Service (2015) ★★★☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/kingsman-the-secret-service-2015/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/kingsman-the-secret-service-2015</id><updated>2015-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kingsman: The Secret Service&lt;/em&gt; tells the story of a young man named Gary who goes by Eggsy. We’re never told how he got this nickname. The film is full of superfluous bits like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eggsy lives with his mother and infant sister in one of London’s ailing housing projects. His father died when he was just a toddler. These days, his mother has taken up with a low-level hood who degrades her and bullies Eggsy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a rare moment of defiance lands Eggsy in jail, Eggsy calls a mysterious number his mother gave him should he ever find himself in trouble. Shortly thereafter, Eggsy walks out of jail a free man. Outside the police station, Eggsy meets Harry Hart. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry, played by Colin Firth, is a dapper gentleman cut from the David Niven cloth. The two go for a pint. Harry tells Eggsy that Eggsy’s father was a Kingsman, a member of an elite group of gentleman super-spies. He died saving Harry’s life. Eggsy is incredulous until he sees Harry take down a group of young thugs using nothing but an umbrella. Before he leaves, Harry offers Eggsy a chance to try out for the Kingsmen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Eggsy goes to spy-school. In keeping with the dapper gentleman theme, spy-school is more like boarding school than boot camp. When they&amp;#39;re not practicing with sniper rifles or parachuting out of planes, the fresh-faced recruits wear uniforms resembling flannel suit pajamas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, every spy story needs a super villain. Here we’re given Richmond Valentine, played by Samuel L. Jackson. Valentine is an internet billionaire who speaks with a lisp, hates the sight of blood, and dresses like a teenager. Convinced mankind is a virus doomed to destroy the planet, Valentine plans to wipe out eighty-five percent of the human race. Naturally, he’ll pick the fifteen percent that will survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And every super villain needs a colorful henchman. Valentine has Gazelle, a double leg amputee whose prosthetics also act as swords capable of slicing a man in half. Spoiler alert: she slices someone in half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the film builds to the inevitable confrontation between Eggsy and Valentine, it becomes increasingly ludicrous. Gazelle dismembers an armed cadre of elite security officers. Harry single-handedly kills a church full of people. Eggsy picks off Valentine’s henchman while somersaulting through the air in slow motion. Heads explode in a rainbow spray of gore. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, it&amp;#39;s silly, but the juxtaposition of the mild mannered Firth and the comical violence leaves the film with nowhere to go but over-the-top. There&amp;#39;s even a scene between Firth and Samuel L. Jackson where they have a black-tie dinner consisting of Big Macs. I can&amp;#39;t imagine anyone but Firth pulling that off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But casting Firth is not without its downsides. With someone like Clive Owen, the film could have gone with a more serious and cynical tone. The script flirts with having something to say about elitism and class hierarchy, but it’s lost amid the silliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, the film is full of superfluous bits. There are characters with no payoff. Roxy, another Kingsmen recruit seems to exist only to make Eggsy seem nicer than the other male recruits. She&amp;#39;s an afterthought by the time we reach the finale. And then there are the plot holes. Like how an ultra secret organization allows most of its recruiting class to walk away after failing to make the cut. Or how an intelligence organization like the Kingsmen doesn’t have its own satellites. This is sloppy storytelling, but one is hard-pressed to care given the film’s relentless spectacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, &lt;em&gt;Kingsman: The Secret Service&lt;/em&gt; is little more than an adolescent male super-spy fantasy. That said, it’s not bad. It&amp;#39;s a throwback to the days when James Bond seemed to relish his job and the films favored adventure over angst. It may not be a great film, but it sure is entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>31. Where Danger Lives (1950) ★☆☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/where-danger-lives-1950/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/where-danger-lives-1950</id><updated>2015-02-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;I usually warn folks when I’m going to spoil plot points, but in the case of &lt;em&gt;Where Danger Lives&lt;/em&gt;, I don&amp;#39;t think it matters. This is one of those films where the hero takes the entire movie to deduce what the audience figures out in the first ten minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film opens with doctor Jeff Cameron treating a little girl. Jeff is telling her a story about elephants. Robert Mitchum plays Jeff. He’s miscast in a part that would better suit Henry Fonda, but that’s the least of the film’s problems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing with the little girl, Jeff clocks out, eager for  his date with Julie, a nice nurse who works at the hospital. But Jeff has to cancel after he&amp;#39;s called to assist with a new patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patient is Margo, a not-so-wholesome girl who’d just attempted suicide. Jeff treats Margo, then the two start dating. He falls hard. Faith Domergue plays Margo. Like Mitchum, she’s miscast. But unlike Mitchum, it’s hard to overlook just how wrong she is for the role. To be fair, it’s a hard part to play. 
Margo has to do more than seduce Jeff, she has to seduce the entire audience. We have to buy Jeff overlooking a myriad of red flags and throwing his life away for a woman he just met. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we don’t buy it. The entire romance is unconvincing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon Margo breaks it to Jeff that she has to leave for Nassau. It seems her father has come home, and upon finding out about Jeff, decided it best that Margo take a trip. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff doesn’t take it well. He has a few too many and goes to Margo’s house. He confronts her father, Mr. Lannington, played by third-billed Claude Rains in his only scene. Here, Jeff discovers the first of many things we already suspected. Lannington isn&amp;#39;t her father at all, but her husband!&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff and Lannington get into a scuffle. Jeff knocks down Lannington who gets back up and pummels Jeff with a fireplace poker. Jeff clocks Lannington, knocking him out cold. Jeff, still reeling, stumbles to the bathroom for some water. When he returns, Margo tells Jeff that Lannington is dead.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, at this point it&amp;#39;s obvious to us that Margo killed her husband while Jeff was out of the room. But, since the rest of the film hinges on Jeff believing he did it, a series of contrived plot machinations are necessary. As the film rolls on the pair will ”just miss&amp;quot; the news. The car radio won’t work. Someone will draw a beard on Margo’s police picture, preventing her from being recognized. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Margo convinces Jeff to make a run for the Mexico border. Jeff agrees. The film explains this by having Jeff tell us he has a concussion. This is the worst concussion you&amp;#39;ve ever seen. Jeff blacks out, loses the ability to think straight, and by the time the film&amp;#39;s predictable conclusion rolls around, finds the left side of his body paralyzed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here the film shifts to a road movie. Margo and Jeff prowl through the small, out-of-the-way towns of the southwest and descend into a kind of backwoods hell. In one town they’re nearly thrown in jail after a fender-bender with a drunken immigrant. In another they’re brought before the town sheriff for being clean shaven during “Whiskers Week.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the film tells us that Margo is crazy. It’s played as a big reveal, but we’ve known it all along. After all, didn’t Jeff meet her because she’d tried to commit suicide? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything wraps up near the Mexico border. Jeff and Margo are holed up in a dingy hotel room. Margo reveals she’d been stashing Lannington’s money in a Mexican bank. Jeff finally realizes that Margo killed Lannington. Margo smothers Jeff with a pillow and heads for the border. She’s almost across when she sees Jeff shambling down the street toward her. She begs him to stop, to not come any further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domergue doesn’t look like a desperate woman, she looks like an actress unsure of what to do. “Don’t make me shoot,” she says to no one as she pulls a small revolver from her purse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff keeps coming. Margo shoots and misses. The border guards shoot Margo, who dies, but not before confessing to the authorities that she killed Lannington alone. Jeff wakes up in a hospital. He’s going to be okay. Julie is there waiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where Danger Lives&lt;/em&gt; isn’t as awful as it is frustrating. The film treats us like simpletons, expecting us to swallow one trite plot twist after another while ignoring Domergue’s stilted performance. I tried, but I just couldn’t do it. Maybe a concussion would have helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cue ominous music: &lt;em&gt;Duh-duh-dum!&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>30. Curse of the Crimson Altar (1968) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/curse-of-the-crimson-altar-1968/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/curse-of-the-crimson-altar-1968</id><updated>2015-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Curse of the Crimson Altar&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;The Crimson Cult&lt;/em&gt; here in the USA) has a good cast, but it is not a good film. This is evident from the opening scene. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A droning hum whines in and out as a young man named Peter Manning stands wearing a suit. He looks dazed. In front of him, a nude woman suffers a whip while lying strapped to a table. Men in black robes look on. One has a goat. Wearing a large headdress complete with ram horns, a green-skinned Barbra Steel introduces herself as Lavinia, the &amp;quot;Keeper of the Black Secret”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. She asks if Peter knows why he&amp;#39;s there. He does. She asks if he&amp;#39;s ready to sign. He is. A man brings over a large book and Peter signs his name. Then Lavinia hands Peter a dagger. Peter stabs the girl on the table. There&amp;#39;s a quick-cut to the goat, which seems distressed. Lavinia snaps her fingers. There&amp;#39;s a crack of thunder. A muscular man dressed in a leather bikini bottom, leather arm-bands, and a studded leather cap sprouting deer antlers brings over a branding iron which he presses into Peter&amp;#39;s chest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, that happens. The film packs a few more of these trippy, S&amp;amp;M-tinged sequences, but they exist more-or-less outside the main narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story concerns Peter&amp;#39;s brother, Robert, played by Mark Eden. When Peter doesn&amp;#39;t return home, Robert goes looking for him at his last known location, a remote country estate called Craxton Lodge. Robert&amp;#39;s arrival coincides with a local festival celebrating the burning of the witch Lavinia some three hundred years earlier. The estate’s owner, J.D. Morely, played by Christopher Lee, claims to have never heard of Peter, but invites Robert to stay on to continue his search. Robert agrees. Robert also meets another of the locals, Professor Marsh, played by Boris Karloff. Marsh, conveniently, is an expert on witchcraft. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the film unwinds, the tone veers between cult conspiracy and Scooby-Doo mystery. Robert discovers secret doors and a fake spiderweb machine en-route to learning the truth behind his brother’s disappearance. But by the time the credits roll we&amp;#39;re left wondering if the scenes with Lavinia were meant to be real or imagined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes ambiguity helps a film resonate. But in this case, it only serves to underscore the film&amp;#39;s patronizing approach to its horror elements. Consider the poor attempt at meta-humor. When one of the characters compares Craxton Lodge to “one of those old houses in horror films,” Robert replies, “It’s like Boris Karloff’s going to pop up at any moment.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first viewing of &lt;em&gt;The Curse of the Crimson Altar&lt;/em&gt; , I considered it something of a guilty pleasure. The over-the-top dream sequences and gratuitous nudity were good for a chuckle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But watching it a second time, I found the film far less entertaining. Sure, Karloff is great. Even wheelchair-bound at eighty-years-old, he could still command a scene. But that’s about all this movie has going for it. Lee’s role gives him little to do, and Barbara Steele is wasted. The story’s mystery elements, already weak on the first viewing, border on tedious the second time around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that this was one of Karloff’s final films, it’s probably required viewing for any serious fan of classic horror. Just don&amp;#39;t watch it a second time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record, there is no &lt;em&gt;Crimson&lt;/em&gt; Altar or &lt;em&gt;Crimson&lt;/em&gt; Cult. &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>29. The Town That Dreaded Sundown (2014) ★★★☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-town-that-dreaded-sundown-2014/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-town-that-dreaded-sundown-2014</id><updated>2015-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown&lt;/em&gt; starts with a prologue recounting a series of unsolved murders that occurred in Texarkana in 1946. It talks about how those killings formed the basis for the original film, &lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown (1976)&lt;/em&gt;, which screens every Halloween somewhere in Texarkana. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film opens on one of those screenings. It&amp;#39;s a drive-in. The camera pans down to a teen couple sitting on the hood of a car. He seems into the film, but she looks uneasy. She says it’s not her kind of movie. He asks her if she wants to go. She does, and they head out. As they leave, the camera picks up a preacher imploring the patrons to remember that people really died back in 1946.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The couple head out for a quiet, deserted area where they can be alone. He makes small talk as they drive. The camera shows them at a tilted angle. It&amp;#39;s an on-the-nose gimmick that foreshadows one of the film&amp;#39;s biggest weaknesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon they&amp;#39;re parked. They start kissing, but the girl spots a man in the nearby woods. He&amp;#39;s dressed just like the killer from the movie. But this is no prank. The man breaks the car&amp;#39;s window with the butt of a revolver. He orders them out of the car at gunpoint, then forces the girl to turn around while he stabs the boy to death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we&amp;#39;re off and running. By genre definitions, the film is a slasher, but I&amp;#39;m always hesitant to use that term. For many people, that equates to the &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; series of films, which were, for the most part, more monster and survival-horror films than slasher. &lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown&lt;/em&gt; is more of a violent mystery. Victims are stalked and murdered in a brutal but stylish manner and we work along with the protagonist to deduce the killer&amp;#39;s identity from a number of suspects. To that end, &lt;em&gt;The Town That Dreaded Sundown&lt;/em&gt; may be the first rural giallo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a lot to like. The supporting cast includes Edward Herrmann as the aforementioned preacher, and Gary Cole as a sheriff’s deputy.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script’s meta-sequel approach works well. It avoids the trap of aggrandizing the original film by regulating it to well-researched pulp entertainment. Granted, this film does play as something of a remake, but by excising the original’s head-scratching bits of comic relief, this entry crafts a much taunter narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the film is far from perfect. Remember the gimmick shot I mentioned earlier? The movie is full of them. Some of them work, but their impact is lost in the shuffle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the scene, set at night, where a woman flees the killer into a huge wheat field. The killer has a gun. He fires and she drops to the ground amid the wheat. He approaches, but can’t find the body. Cut to a bird’s eye shot of the field and we see the woman crawling away from the killer as he stalks forward. They’re not more than six feet apart, but they can’t see each other. The shot’s only held for a few moments before we cut back to a tight shot of the killer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? That was a great shot. Keep it. Cut the music. Just give us the sound of the wind and let us watch from above as she crawls, hoping against hope that he doesn’t see her. Their meeting is inevitable, but the tension would have been palpable watching the two skew towards one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the ending. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we get to that, let me say that I liked the movie. The location photography, colorful supporting cast, and competent script make for a solid little slasher. So, having said that, and having given you a sense of what the film is about and what it’s like, I feel my job as reviewer is done. If you want to stop reading here, I’ll understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still with me? Okay. I didn’t love the ending. I didn’t hate it either, but I did feel like it felt like a missed opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why. The script touches on the notion of violence inspired by the media several times, but only in passing. I felt like the film was really building to something however, and when the heroine makes to leave town with her grandmother, it struck me. What if this is the end of the movie? She leaves, the killer is never caught. All the bits about inspired violence coalesce into a biting commentary. The killer will be there as long as he has an audience. It would even dovetail nicely with the original&amp;#39;s ambiguous ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, some folks would hate it, but I bet a lot of theater-goers hated the original’s ending too. And yet, that ending helped the original resonate enough to inspire a remake almost forty years later.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>28. The Big Steal (1949) ★★★★☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-big-steal-1949/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-big-steal-1949</id><updated>2015-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Like any good script, &lt;em&gt;The Big Steal&lt;/em&gt; starts as late into the story as possible. Aboard an ocean liner that&amp;#39;s just docked in Veracruz, Mexico, William Bendix bursts into Robert Mitchum&amp;#39;s cabin holding a gun. He&amp;#39;s after something he believes Mitchum stole. Mitchum says he doesn&amp;#39;t have it. “You’ve got the wrong man,” Mitchum says. Bendix isn’t buying it. He moves to arrest Mitchum. Mitchum overpowers Bendix, knocking him out. Mitchum takes Bendix&amp;#39;s gun and identification. The identification reads: Captain Vincent Blake of the US Army. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After debarking, Mitchum crosses paths with Jane Greer. It&amp;#39;s a short meeting, as Mitchum has to duck out of sight as Bendix emerges from the ship. Once the coast is clear, Mitchum tries to catch a cab, only to find Greer has gotten the last one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cut to a room inside the Hotel Mexico. We see Patric Knowles packing. He’s in a rush. His eyes are darting around. There&amp;#39;s a knock at the door. Knowles pulls a gun and moves to the side of the door, ready to plug whoever comes in. Then we hear Greer&amp;#39;s voice, telling him to open up. We learn that Knowles is Greer&amp;#39;s fiancee. But she&amp;#39;s not there to marry him, she&amp;#39;s there because he ran off with her savings, about two thousand dollars. She wants it back. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowles tries to sweet talk her, but Greer cuts him off saying, &amp;quot;The last time you did that it cost me my bank account.&amp;quot; Knowles tries to make her feel bad for harping on him about the money saying, &amp;quot;There&amp;#39;s that dollar sign again.&amp;quot; But Greer snaps back, &amp;quot;Where? I don&amp;#39;t see it. Come on, hand it over.&amp;quot; Then, dripping with sarcasm, &amp;quot;I was saving that money for my trousseau.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowles gives Greer the slip, and a few beats later we learn that Mitchum is after Knowles too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the film is set. It’s one big chase. Bendix chases Mitchum who, along with Greer, chases Knowles. Mitchum and Greer form an uneasy partnership as they travel across the Mexican countryside from Veracruz to Tehuacán&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  As the story unfolds we learn what was stolen, and who did the stealing. Mitchum and Greer warm to each other. Everything culminates in a surprising, but satisfying finale. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On paper, it&amp;#39;s another forgettable lower-budget entry from RKO, the once premier studio that had fallen to disarray under Howard Hughes. But thanks to a crackerjack script, &lt;em&gt;The Big Steal&lt;/em&gt; is better than it probably had any right to be. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script is a thing of beauty. Consider how little information we&amp;#39;re given as the movie begins. Rather than open with a flashback or exposition, we’re thrown right into one unnamed man confronting another over an event we know nothing about. That’s great storytelling. But it’s when Greer confronts Knowles that the script really sparkles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s refreshing to see such an independent female character. She&amp;#39;s self assured without being arrogant. Insistent without being whiny. The script may leave the fisticuffs to the male characters, but Greer&amp;#39;s character holds her own in the numerous bouts of verbal sparring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script also does a great job of subverting our expectations. From the anything-but-inept Mexican police inspector, to Greer—not Mitchum—being the one to get them out of various jams, the script defies the genre’s conventions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And topping it all off, there&amp;#39;s a nice touch where Mitchum actually wears some of the results of his tussles. From a bloody nose to a beaten face, the film’s fights have visible consequences. Something all too rare in Hollywood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, it&amp;#39;s not a perfect film. The extended car chase feels tacked on and forced. And Knowles and Bendix don&amp;#39;t quite hold their own against Mitchum and Greer in terms of star wattage. But really, these are weaknesses instead of faults. &lt;em&gt;The Big Steal&lt;/em&gt; takes a B-movie plot and elevates it to near greatness thanks to a well-crafted script peppered with crackling dialog. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They actually shot in Mexico, which helps to belie the film’s modest budget.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>27. Rasputin: The Mad Monk (1966) ★★☆☆☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/rasputin-the-mad-monk-1966/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/rasputin-the-mad-monk-1966</id><updated>2015-01-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rasputin: The Mad Monk&lt;/em&gt; opens with Rasputin, played by Christopher Lee, arriving at an inn and demanding wine. When he&amp;#39;s told the innkeeper is unavailable due to his ill wife, an annoyed Rasputin marches upstairs. He storms into the bedroom, and proceeds to &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; the disease out of the frail woman, drawing it into his now red-hot hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dancing and merriment follow. Rasputin gets good and drunk and takes the innkeeper&amp;#39;s daughter out to the barn. This doesn&amp;#39;t sit well with her young suitor who brawls with Rasputin. Rasputin chops the young lad&amp;#39;s hand off saying, &amp;quot;He won&amp;#39;t trouble us anymore,&amp;quot; then makes to get back with the daughter. But the wounded suitor brings the rest of the village, who chase Rasputin out of town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great introduction. If only the rest of the film lived up to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the story unfolds, Rasputin travels to Saint Petersburg. There he insinuates himself into the Tsaritsa&amp;#39;s court by hypnotizing one of her ladies-in-waiting. Barbara Shelley plays the lady in question. There&amp;#39;s a good bit where Rasputin, having just hypnotized Shelley&amp;#39;s character into sleeping with him, tells her to leave some money on the dresser. As Rasputin&amp;#39;s influence grows, members of the court begin to conspire against him. There&amp;#39;s an overly elaborate plot involving poison, some grappling, then it&amp;#39;s all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a terrific performance by Lee, and Hammer&amp;#39;s solid production values&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the film underwhelms. It treats the character of Rasputin as a one-dimensional monster. This wouldn’t be so bad, but the talky script vacillates between biographical drama and horror without committing to either.  The result? Rasputin spends too much time drinking and dancing and not enough time chopping off hands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, they spliced in a ballroom shot from &lt;em&gt;Anastasia (1956)&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>26. The Devil Rides Out (1968) ★★★★☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-devil-rides-out-1968/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-devil-rides-out-1968</id><updated>2015-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Some films have no business working as well as they do. &lt;em&gt;The Devil Rides Out&lt;/em&gt; is one such film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set in 1929, the story opens with the dashing Duke de Richleau awaiting the arrival of his good friend, Rex Van Ryn. The Duke is played by Hammer stalwart Christopher Lee who, in a rare change of pace, gets to play the hero and does a fine job of it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rex arrives piloting his own biplane, which is the extent of the characterization the script allots him.  After landing, he and the Duke set out to call on their young friend, Simon. What they find upon arriving at Simon&amp;#39;s palatial house alarms the Duke. It seems Simon has fallen in with a group of Satanists led by the sinister Mocata, played by Charles Gray. As the Duke says, “Simon is playing the most dangerous game known to mankind.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lee’s dialog is full of lines like that. They should induce groans, but Lee pulls them off with flair. He opens the commentary track on the DVD saying that he’s largely responsible for the film being made. He was a big fan of the novel by Dennis Wheatley and brought the book to the attention of studio executives. His performance is reminiscent of Peter Cushing’s turn as Van Helsing in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews/horror-of-dracula-1958/&quot;&gt;Horror of Dracula (1958)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and his admiration of the source material shines through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opposite Lee, Gray delivers a smooth, understated performance that’s almost as magnetic as Lee&amp;#39;s&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Consider the scene where he calls on the Duke&amp;#39;s niece in an attempt to extract Simon. She makes to throw him out, but he leaves of his own accord saying, “I&amp;#39;m leaving. I shall not be back. But something will.” He pauses for a moment then adds, “Tonight. Something will come for Simon and the girl.” His tone is casual, not threatening, and all the more menacing for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the supernatural elements, &lt;em&gt;The Devil Rides Out&lt;/em&gt;  isn’t really a horror movie at all&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It’s a terrific pulp adventure. Sure, the characters are archetypes, and the stilted dialog may induce a wry smirk, but the film rolls along at such a good clip, we’ve hardly a moment to care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gray had just starred in &lt;em&gt;You Only Live Twice (1967)&lt;/em&gt; but Hammer&amp;#39;s first choice for Mocata was another Bond alumnus: Gert Fröbe, Goldfinger himself!&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fearing moviegoers would think &lt;em&gt;The Devil Rides Out&lt;/em&gt; was a western, Twentieth Century Fox changed the title to &lt;em&gt;The Devil&amp;#39;s Bride&lt;/em&gt; for the USA theatrical release.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>25. The One I Love (2014) ★★★★☆</title><link href='http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-one-i-love-2014/' /><id>http://www.franksmovielog.com/reviews/the-one-i-love-2014</id><updated>2015-01-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><content type='html'>&lt;p&gt;Warning: There be spoilers here. It&amp;#39;s not possible to talk about &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; in a meaningful way without them. But it’s a movie best seen with an open mind. So I encourage you, if you haven&amp;#39;t seen it, to do so. It&amp;#39;s not perfect, but the first two acts are brilliant and it&amp;#39;s original enough to warrant a look. Go ahead, I&amp;#39;ll wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back? Okay, here we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Duplass and Elisabeth Moss play Ethan and Sophie, a young couple on the brink of divorce. They&amp;#39;ve drifted apart. Their counselor sends them to a remote retreat for a weekend getaway. He believes it’s just what they need to reconnect and rediscover one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The retreat turns out to be a sizable country estate, complete with pool and guest house. Ethan and Sophie arrive and discover they&amp;#39;re the only people present. They settle in, have a nice dinner, and smoke some marijuana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sophie wanders over to the guest house.  Ethan joins her. They laugh, talk and have a wonderful time. The best they&amp;#39;ve had in years. They have sex. Later, Sophie heads back to the main house to grab some things. Inside, she&amp;#39;s surprised to find Ethan lying on the couch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She laughs and asks how he&amp;#39;s beaten her back. Ethan looks confused. He&amp;#39;s just woken up. Sophie stops laughing. She asks him why he&amp;#39;s acting like this after they just has sex. Ethan looks at her with bewilderment. He tells her he&amp;#39;s been asleep on the couch since they smoked the marijuana. Sophie storms off, furious at Ethan&amp;#39;s unfunny joke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethan wanders over to the guest house and falls asleep on the couch there. In the middle of the night, Sophie joins him. They snuggle. Ethan wakes to find Sophie making breakfast. Including bacon. Sophie hates bacon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to this point, the film has cultivated a subtle aura of menace. The long shadow-filled shots of Sophie walking back to the house and through the empty kitchen wouldn&amp;#39;t seem out of place in a home invasion thriller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now we&amp;#39;ve got an inkling of what&amp;#39;s going on, and to the film&amp;#39;s credit, it doesn&amp;#39;t drag things out.  Ethan and Sophie soon realize that when one of them enters the guest house alone, they&amp;#39;re greeted by a doppelgänger of the other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They run. Again, credit to the film. It&amp;#39;s what most folks would do. But then Ethan and Sophie get to thinking about it. Especially Sophie. They talk. The film&amp;#39;s tone shifts from menacing to quirky. Sophie suggests going back. Weren&amp;#39;t they there to try new things? Ethan agrees. They return to the retreat and set some ground rules for the guest house. Fifteen minute sessions, no intimate activity. Total honesty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, these rules soon go out the window. Sophie begins sneaking out to see the other Ethan. Ethan ends up impersonating his doppelgänger in order to sleep with Sophie. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, Ethan gets some voicemails from friends and family members. The messages suggest that Ethan made a series of calls in the middle of the night asking random questions about his past. Some of his clothes seem to have gone missing as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon the doppelgängers confront Ethan and Sophie as a couple. The four try to have a nice dinner, but Ethan&amp;#39;s suspicion and resentment bubble over. He storms off to the guest house. Once inside, he finds he can&amp;#39;t get out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In time, Sophie&amp;#39;s doppelgänger arrives. Then the film falls apart. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to this point, the doppelgängers felt like a novel device the script employed to visualize Ethan and Sophie&amp;#39;s perceptions of one another. This sort of thing could feel like a gimmick and veer into into cheesy fantasy, but the film stays grounded by focusing on the harsh realities of trying to make a relationship work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end, the doppelgängers require no explanation. They exist to serve the story. The film even floats this notion, suggesting that some things “Just happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the movie isn&amp;#39;t confident enough to leave it at that. And so Sophie&amp;#39;s doppelgänger reveals the truth to Ethan. Her and Doppelgänger Ethan were another couple sent to the retreat like Ethan and Sophie, but now they&amp;#39;re trapped. The only way they can leave is to break up Ethan and Sophie so they can take their place. But something&amp;#39;s gone wrong. The other Ethan has fallen in love with the real Sophie. He&amp;#39;s planning to leave with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that wealth of exposition, the plot kicks in. Doppelgänger Sophie lets Ethan out of the guest house and distracts Doppelgänger Ethan (by posing as the real Sophie) so that Ethan can warn Sophie. When Sophie refuses to leave with him, Doppelgänger Ethan tries leaving by himself. An invisible wall knocks him cold. Ethan and Sophie leave. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next we see, they&amp;#39;re lying in bed giggling. Sophie gets up and offers to make breakfast, asking if Ethan wants bacon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film name-drops &lt;em&gt;The Twilight Zone&lt;/em&gt; but the first two acts are more reminiscent of David Lynch&amp;#39;s work.  Like Lynch&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Lost Highway (1997)&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mulholland Dr. (1999)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; explores the subject of identity through a strange, inexplicable event. But the difference is that in Lynch&amp;#39;s films, the character&amp;#39;s motivations are never explicitly verbalized. If you define them, the rest of the story must serve them. When it doesn’t, you have plot holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And boy does &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; have a lot of them. The whole film does&amp;#39;t make any sense, really. What was the point of imprisoning couples there? Why transform the previous couples into doppelgängers of the next ones? Why can they only leave after the other two have broken up? Why did their therapist send them in the first place? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all this, &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; impressed me. It&amp;#39;s a brilliant concept that&amp;#39;s handled with the perfect tone. That it goes off the rails at the end doesn&amp;#39;t detract from the great performances and it&amp;#39;s biting insight into relationships. The plot holes don’t ruin the movie, they just handicap it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, just imagine if it didn&amp;#39;t try to explain the doppelgängers. Imagine if the scene where Ethan hears the other couple&amp;#39;s voices turning into his and Sophie&amp;#39;s was left out. Imagine if when Ethan confronted doppelgänger Sophie about not being real, she just sat and stared at him with that slightly unnatural smile. Then cut to the scene of Ethan and Sophie back home in bed laughing and Sophie getting up to make breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose this ending would leave some portion of the audience wanting. Lynch’s films are famous for that. They’re like lego sets. They provide the audience with the building blocks of a story, but leave it to the viewer to create their own interpretation and meaning. Unfortunately, &lt;em&gt;The One I Love&lt;/em&gt; is less like a set of legos and more like a puzzle. One that&amp;#39;s missing a few pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>